<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="95"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[MINISTRY OF SCIENCE AND HIGHER EDUCATION OF THE REPUBLIC OF KAZAKHSTAN


                                                                   Non-profit joint stock company
                                                                   “M. Auezov South Kazakhstan
                                                                              University”



                                       G. Zhantureyeva, Zh.Zhussubalina















                                                      TEXTBOOK

                        for undergraduate students in the specialty/educational program
                                           6В02320 – Translation Studies





































                                                    Shymkent 2025]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[УДК 81'25 (075.8)

           ББК 81.2-7 я73
           A13


            Textbook is recommended for publishing by Educational and Methodological
           Council of M. Auezov SKU, minutes № 6 from 25.05.2023.


                 Reviewers:
                  T. Аinabekova  –  Candidate of Philological Sciences, Associate Professor of the
           Department, Associate Professor of the Department of English, South Kazakhstan
           State Pedagogical University
                  A. Suyuberdieva – Candidate of Pedagogical Sciences, Head of the Department
           “English for the Humanities”, South Kazakhstan University named after M. Auezov
                  G. Zhumagulova – Candidate of Philological Sciences, Associate Professor, Head

           of the Department “Foreign Languages”, South Kazakhstan Medical Academy


                G. Zhantureyeva, Zh. Zhussubalina, Translation of publicistic texts/textbook –
           Shymkent: M. Auezov South Kazakhstan university, 2025 – 88 pages.




                The textbook is compiled in accordance with the requirements of the curriculum
           and the program of the discipline "Translation of publicistic texts". The textbook is
           intended  for  undergraduate  students  in  the  specialty/  educational  program
           "Translation Studies". The purpose of this course is the formation and development
           of skills in visual and oral translation of journalistic texts. The textbook is accompanied
           by texts grouped by subject  and  covering the following topics:  Business,  Finance,
           Economics;  Science  and  Technology;  Entertainment  and  Culture;  Health  and

           Medicine;  Sports  and  Recreation;  Lifestyle;  Multicultural  Press;  Trade  and
           Professional; Media in Kazakhstan and the UK.

                                                                                    УДК 81'25 (075.8)

                                                                                       ББК 81.2-7 я73




                                                    © M. Auezov South Kazakhstan university, 2025]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[CONTEXT




                                                    INTRODUCTION



                                  UNIT 1. BUSINESS, FINANCE & ECONOMICS



                                        UNIT 2. SCIENCE & TECHNOLOGY



                                  UNIT 3. ENTERTAINMENT, ART & CULTURE



                                           UNIT 4. HEALTH & MEDICINE



                                UNIT 5. GENERAL NEWS & CURRENT AFFAIRS



                                             UNIT 6. SPORT & LEISURE



                                                  UNIT 7. LIFESTYLE



                                         UNIT 8. MULTICULTURAL PRESS



                                         UNIT 9. TRADE & PROFESSIONAL



                                               UNIT 10. KZ/UK MEDIA



                                                      REFERENCES






















                                                              3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[INTRODUCTION


                  The textbook "Translation of publicistic texts" is designed for students of  M.
           Auezov, who are starting to study the aspect of journalistic translation within the
           framework of the curriculum - translation of publicistic texts, the European level of
           language proficiency B-1 - B-2.
                  The  purpose  of  the  textbook  is  to  develop  practical  translation  skills  from
           English  into  Russian  and  vice  versa;  creation  of  translation  competence  among

           students; preparation of future specialists for professional written translation.
                  The  manual  consists  of  10  parts.  Each  part  contains  authentic  texts  of
           journalistic content from current English-language publications for the period 2022-
           2023. The texts can be used for interpreting in class, as well as for written translation
           at home. The selection of texts and the system of lexical tasks for them are made
           taking into account the communicative orientation of teaching English, as well as
           improving the skills and abilities of translating texts on various topics.

                  The sources of the presented materials are international news sites such as:
           VOA News, NBC News, BBC News, The Guardian, SKY News, Inform KZ. Topics of the
           ten sections are as follows: Business, Finance & Economics; Science & Technology;
           Entertainment, Arts & Culture; Health & Medicine; General News & Current News;
           Sports & Leisure; Lifestyle; Multicultural press; Professional and Trade; Media in KZ
           and UK.
                  The  proposed  manual  will  help  students  expand  their  vocabulary  by
           replenishing  it  with  words  and  expressions  that  are  absent  in  most  of  the  basic

           manuals, but are constantly heard in modern English speech. This allowance can be
           used both independently and in combination with other allowances provided by the
           programs.
                  The authors hope that this textbook will be useful for all students and will help
           them effectively and efficiently carry out both oral and written translations.





















                                                          4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[UNIT I. BUSINESS, FINANCE &ECONOMICS


                                                          TEXT 1

                           Tunisia orders top European Trade Union official expelled

                     TUNIS  — President  Kais  Saied  of  Tunisia  ordered  Europe's  top  trade  union

              official  to  leave  the  North  African  country  after  she  addressed  protesters  at  a
              demonstration organized by an influential labor union.
                     Authorities accused Esther Lynch, the Irish general secretary of the European
              Trade  Union  Confederation,  of  making  statements  that  “interfered  with  Tunisian
              internal affairs” during a Saturday protest against Saied in the port city of Sfax.
                     Tunisia's  General  Labor  Union,  or  UGTT,  organized  the  demonstration  to
              protest a crackdown on the increasingly authoritarian president's political opponents

              and his critics in the media, judiciary, business community and trade unions.
                     In an address to the protesters, Lynch demanded the release of union leader
              Anis Kaabi, who was arrested by security forces last month.
                     She called on the Tunisian government to negotiate with the UGTT leadership
              and to improve the economy, which has teetered on the brink of bankruptcy amid
              political instability that deepened after a parliamentary election last month in which
              only 11% of voters cast ballots.
                     “By orders of the president, Tunisian authorities ordered Esther Lynch to leave

              the  country  within  24  hours,  following  statements  made  during  the  UGTT-led
              demonstration that interfered with Tunisian internal affairs,” said a statement by the
              Tunisian presidency that was posted on Twitter late Saturday.
                     The European Trade Union Confederation confirmed that Lynch left Tunisia on
              Sunday.
                     Saied won the presidency in a 2019 landslide on a promise to improve the

              country's  economy.  Instead,  the  president  appears  determined  to  upend  the
              country's political system, threatening a democracy once seen as a model for the Arab
              world and sending the economy toward a tailspin.
                     In December, the International Monetary Fund froze an agreement on a $1.9
              billion loan for Tunisia. The deeply indebted government needs  the funds  to pay
              UGTT-represented public sector salaries and to fill budget gaps aggravated by the
              COVID-19 pandemic and the fallout from Russia's war in Ukraine.
                     In  recent  months,  Tunisians  have  been  hit  with  soaring  food  prices  and
              shortages of fuel and basic staples like sugar and vegetable oil.


              Link:  https://www.voanews.com/a/tunisia-orders-top-european-trade-union-official
              expelled/6969715.html


                                                              5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[VOCABULARY


            order, to order                                 promise, to promise
            trade, to trade                                 government, to govern
            address, to address                             fund, to fund
            organization, to organize                       confirmation, to confirm
            protest, to protest                             threat, to threaten
            demonstration, to demonstrate                   release, to release
            influence, to influence                         determination, to determine

            accusation, to accuse                           opponents
            statement, to state                             European Trade Union Confederation
            interference, to interfere                      UGTT
            arrest, to arrest                               Tunisia
            critics, to criticize                           Sfax
            demand, to demand                               judiciary

            call, to call                                   International Monetary Fund
            force, to force                                 tailspin
            improvement, to improve                         budget gaps
            vote, to vote                                   food prices
            election, to elect                              basic staples
            negotiation, negotiate




           Answer the questions:
           1. What did the president of Tunisia order? Who was the order addressed to?
           2. What is Esther Lynch accused for?
           3. What did Tunisia’s General Labor Union (UGTT) organize?
           4. What did Lynch demand in an address to the protestors?
           5.  Do think that economy of Tunisia has improved since 2019?


                                                       NOTES
           European Trade Union Confederation - the biggest trade union group representing
           worker interests in Europe.
           UGTT (Union Générale Tunisienne du Travail) - the Tunisian national union trade
           center.
           International Monetary Fund - is a significant financial institution of the UN and a
           global financial organization with its headquarters in Washington, D.C. It includes 190

           nations. Its stated goal is to "work to promote high employment and sustainable
           economic  development,  secure  financial  stability,  ease  international  trade,  and
           reduce poverty throughout the world.


                                                          6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[COVID-19 – Coronavirus disease - The SARS-CoV-2 virus is the infectious illness known

              as  coronavirus  disease  (COVID-19).  The  majority  of  virus-infected  individuals  will
              experience a mild to moderate respiratory illness and will heal without the need for
              special care. However, some people will develop severe illnesses and need to see a
              doctor.
              Tunisia - is a country in North Africa, whose natural borders are the Mediterranean
              Sea and the Sahara desert.
              Russia - Russia is a federal presidential-parliamentary republic that stretches over a
              vast expanse of Eastern Europe and Northern Asia.

              Ukraine – is the biggest country in Eastern Europe and the second – largest European
              country. It is a unitary state and mixed republic.
              Sfax - a city located 270 kilometers southeast of Tunisia's capital. On the site of the
              Roman settlement of Taparura, the city was established in 849.
              Twitter – is an American microblogging service and social network in which users post
              and interact with messages known as "tweets".


              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
              Trade union; official; influential labor union; general secretary; internal affairs; port
              city; to interfere; to protest a crackdown; political opponents; business community;
              the release of union leader; media. Judiciary; protesters; union leader; security forces;
              to negotiate; the brink of bankruptcy; political instability; parliamentary election; cast
              ballots; presidency; political system; to fill the budget; COVID-19 pandemic; win the
              presidency; to threaten a democracy; to freeze an agreement; public sector; soaring

              food prices; shortages of fuel; basic staples.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              Приказать; профсоюзный деятель; покинуть страну; обратиться к протестующим;
              генеральный  секретарь;  организовать  демонстрацию;  в  знак  протеста;
              политические  противники;  силы  безопасности;  проводить  переговоры;
              политическая  нестабильность;  вмешиваться  во  внутренние  дела;  улучшить

              экономику;  погрязшее  в  долгах  правительство;  государственный  сектор;
              последствия войны; восполнение бюджетных пробелов.

              C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
              Example:
                                                               work;  toil;  employment;  industry;
               Labor                                           exertion;  drudgery;  effort;  activity;
                                                               energy; job; chore; endeavor.


               Opponent



                                                              7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Democracy


            Budget


            Authority



            Election


            Salary



            Economy



                                                       TEXT 2


              Etsy warns sellers of delay in processing payments due to Silicon Valley Bank
                                                      collapse

                  One affected Etsy seller said the deposits delay would have a "catastrophic"
           effect on his business.
                  Etsy  is  warning  sellers  that  the collapse  of  Silicon  Valley  Bank on  Friday  is
           causing  delays  in  processing  payments,  according  to  an  email  from  the  company

           shared with NBC News.
                  The  online  do-it-yourself  goods  mega  shop  said  it  used  SVB  to  facilitate
           disbursement to some sellers, and that it was working with other payment partners
           to issue deposits.
                  "We wanted to let you know that there is a delay with your deposit that was
           scheduled for today," the email from Etsy said.
                  "We know that you count on us to help run your business and we understand
           how important it is for you to receive your funds when you need them," the email

           continued. "Please know that our teams are working hard to resolve this issue and
           send you your funds as quickly as possible."
                  In  a  written  statement  Saturday,  an  Etsy  spokesperson  said  the  issue  was
           related to "the unexpected collapse of Silicon Valley Bank."


                                                          8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[The company said in the statement it has been working on a solution, "and we

              expect to pay sellers via our other payment partners within the next several business
              days."
                     Etsy claims  7.5  million  sellers  worldwide. Regulators  placed  SVB  into
              receivership around noon Friday to end a bank run on the tech lender that had begun
              Wednesday after it said it was seeking to raise more than $2 billion.
                     Etsy seller Owen McKinney said the deposits delay would have a "catastrophic"
              effect on his business.
                     McKinney, who runs Kentucky Country Home laser engraving business, said in

              an  email  that  he  relies  on  the  deposits  to  pay  for  items  like  shipping  costs  and
              materials. He said he had already reached out to one of his suppliers to delay an order
              for materials that he needed for next week.
                     "At this time, Etsy has not provided a time frame for the funds to be deposited,"
              McKinney said. "While I do have a website, Etsy remains a huge part of my business."
                     Another  Etsy  seller,  Rachel  Briggs,  has  been  on  Etsy  since  2010  selling  her

              designs: enamel pins, keychains, and handmade art dolls. Briggs quit her office job in
              2020 and has since been a freelance artist. She said her business on Etsy, in addition
              to her work as an illustrator, is a “huge part” of her household’s income.
                     Recently, Briggs paid for an “expensive” tax appointment with a professional to
              handle the documentation now that her income is less traditional. She expected her
              Etsy deposit would cover the cost.
                     “Getting the email that one of my most anticipated deposits is being delayed
              was not really a good thing to wake up to,” Briggs said. Part of her Etsy sales occurred

              before the deposit was held up, she added, allowing her to pay for the tax services.
                     Nina Bissett, another  Etsy seller, has  relied  on the platform as  her primary
              source of income since being laid off. Her business is a curated selection of vintage
              home goods, handmade, disco balls, and accessories.
                     When she got the email about the delay in payment, she felt worried for herself
              and the thousands of other sellers.
                     “My customers are still expecting their orders, and I won’t be able to use the

              funds I was expecting to use to pay for shipping and materials,” Bissett said.
                     “It will  effectively limit how much extra inventory I can hold and sell,” she
              added.
                     She said she's hopeful the issue will be resolved soon.
                     The drama with SVB started earlier this week when the bank disclosed that
              it sold about $21 billion of securities and proposed to offer over $1 billion in shares,
              all to fundraise for “general corporate purposes.”
                     That move raised eyebrows among investors who pondered why SVB would

              need to raise so much money abruptly. It also worried depositors, many of whom
              suddenly wondered whether their money was safe and began pulling funds out.
                     On Friday, the California Department of Financial Protection and Innovation
              said  that  it  was taking  over  and  closing  SVB to  protect  deposits,  naming  the
                                                              9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation as its receiver. The FDIC has formed a

           separate entity where all insured SVB deposits — up to $250,000 per depositor — will
           be available by Monday morning.
                  The shutdown came after a tumultuous morning for SVB, during which trading
           of its shares was halted after they fell by double-digits before markets opened. That
           downslide came on the heels of a more than 60% decline Thursday.
                  The closure marks the biggest bank failure since the 2008 financial crisis and
           the  second-largest  in  U.S.  history  after Washington  Mutual  collapsed during  that
           industry-wide meltdown, according to FDIC data.


           Link:     https://www.nbcnews.com/business/business-news/etsy-delays-payments-
           sellers-due-silicon-valley-bank-collapse-rcna74475

           VOCABULARY


            delay, to delay                                 fund, to fund
            collapse, to collapse                           regulators, to regulate
            cause, to cause                                 end, to end
            facilities, to facilitate                       design, to design
            processing, to process                          an expectation, to expect
            limit, to limit                                 offer, to offer
            payment, to pay                                 proposal, to propose
            illustration, illustrator, to illustrate        shares, to share

            count, to count                                 decline, to decline
            cover, to cover                                 trade, to trade
            work, to work                                   halt, to halt


                                                       NOTES
           Silicon Valley Bank - a commercial bank that was part of the financial group SVB

           Financial Group.
           NBC News - The US television news channel, owned by the National Broadcasting
           Company, began operations on February 21, 1940.
           The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (FSIC) - is a US federal agency created by
           Congress in 1933 to insure deposits placed  in bank accounts. The FDIC covers  all
           Federal Reserve banks and other lending institutions.
           U.S. - The United States of America is a 50-state country that occupies a significant
           part of North America.

           Washington Mutual, Inc. - banking holding that existed from 1889 to 2008. Its largest
           branch  was  the  Washington  Mutual  Savings  Bank,  the  largest  savings  and  loan
           association in the United States. The bank was founded in 1889 in Seattle as a loan
           and investment association.
                                                         10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[California Department of Financial Protection and Innovation - regulates a range of

              financial services, companies, products, and professionals. It was formerly known as
              the Department of Business Oversight (DBO).

              A. Scan the reading passage on pages 7-9 and answer the questions.
              1. What is Etsy?  ____________________________________________________
              2. How many sellers worldwide does Etsy claim to have? ___________________
              3. What caused the delay in processing the payments?_______________________


              B. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
              "catastrophic" effect; collapse of Silicon Valley Bank; online do-it-yourself goods; to
              facilitate disbursement to some sellers; to issue deposits; delay with one’s deposit;
              unexpected collapse; payment partners; run one’s business; several business days;
              shipping costs and materials; to delay an order; a time frame; household’s income;
              tax  appointment;  cover  the  cost;  general  corporate  purposes;  to  come  on  heels;

              tumultuous; trade shares; downslide; financial crisis; industry-wide meltdown.

              C. Find in the text the English for:
              Пострадавший продавец; задержка депозита; «катастрофическое» влияние на
              бизнес;  крах;  задержки  в  обработке  платежей;  интернет-магазин;  платежные
              партнеры;  рассчитывать  на  помощь;  команды  прилагают  все  усилия;
              письменное  заявление;  рабочие  дни;  продавцы  по  всему  миру;  поставщик;
              отменить заказ; сроки внесения средств; вызвать недоумение среди инвесторов;

              продать ценные бумаги на сумму около  21 миллиарда долларов; обеспокоить
              вкладчиков; крупнейшее банкротство;  финансовый кризис; второе по величине
              в истории США.

              D. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
              Example:
                                                               Merchant; vendor; trader; salesperson;

               Seller                                          retailer; stockiest; dealer; salesman;
                                                               saleswoman; purveyor; shopkeeper.

               Shares



               Decline


               Payment



                                                             11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Crisis


            Collapse


            Solution



            Income



           F. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on page 7-9. Read the words

           around them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts
           below to make definitions:


            1. A team                                       a. is a person or organization that puts
                                                            money into financial schemes, property,
                                                            etc. with the expectation of achieving a
                                                            profit.

            2. An investor                                  b.   is  compulsory  financial  charge  or
                                                            some other type of levy imposed on a
                                                            taxpayer       by      a     governmental
                                                            organization      in    order     to    fund
                                                            government spending
            3. If you are hopeful                           c. believe that (someone or something)
                                                            will arrive soon.
            4. A tax                                        d.  you  feel  optimistic  about  a  future

                                                            event.
            5. If you expect something                      e. is a group of people working together
                                                            in order to achieve something.


           E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:

            to come on heels                                to cover the cost

            to run one’s business                           financial crisis
            to solve an issue                               primary source of income
            a shipping cost                                 an unexpected collapse
            a time frame                                    to delay one’s order

                                                         12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[UNIT II. SCIENCE & TECHNOLOGY


                                                              TEXT 1

                     Wind and solar generated a record amount of global power in 2022
                     Record  growth  in  wind  and  solar  last  year  pushed  worldwide  electricity
              generation to its cleanest-ever level, a report found, reflecting a renewable energy

              boom that researchers say could herald the “beginning of the end of the fossil age.”
                     The analysis published Wednesday by independent climate think tank Ember
              found that 12% of the world’s power came from solar and wind in 2022, up from 10%
              of global electricity generation in 2021.
                     Solar  was the fastest-growing source of  electricity for the 18th consecutive
              year, the report said, rising by 24% year-on-year and adding enough power to meet
              the annual electricity demand of South Africa.

                     The report found that the increase in wind generation, which added 17% in
              2022, could have powered almost all of the U.K.
                     “We  are  entering  the  clean  power  era,”  said  Małgorzata  Wiatros-Motyka,
              senior electricity analyst at Ember and lead author of the research. “The stage is set
              for wind and solar to achieve a meteoric rise to the top. Clean electricity will reshape
              the global economy, from transport to industry and beyond.”
                     Wiatros-Motyka added, “A new era of falling fossil emissions means the coal
              power phasedown will happen, and the end of gas power growth is now within sight.”

                     Researchers said that the analysis — which was based on electricity data from
              78 countries last year and represents 93% of global power demand — provides the
              first accurate picture of the electricity transition in 2022.
                     It shows that more than 60 countries now generate over 10% of their electricity
              from wind and solar.
                     Renewables and nuclear sources were collectively found to have accounted for

              39% of global electricity generation in 2022 — in a new record high.
                     Despite this progress, researchers said that the dramatic build-out of wind and
              solar was still not fast enough to fulfil all of the world’s increasing electricity needs.
              Consequently, the report noted that coal and other fossil fuels met the remaining
              gap, driving up emissions to a new record high.
                     Coal, the world’s dirtiest fossil fuel, was found to be the single largest source of
              electricity worldwide last year, producing 36% of global power.
                     Burning fossil fuels, such as coal, oil and gas, is the chief driver of the climate
              emergency.

                     “Much more needs to be done to ensure that developing countries are not left
              behind and locked into high carbon futures,” said Damilola Ogunbiyi, CEO and special
              representative of the U.N. Secretary-General for Sustainable Energy for All.
                     Ogunbiyi said the fact that coal power remained the single largest source of
              electricity worldwide last year reaffirmed the point that the power sector is off track
                                                             13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[to meet net-zero targets. “The deployment of wind and solar needs to be massively

           and urgently accelerated.”
                  The Ember report said that 2022 may come to mark the peak of electricity
           emissions and the final year of fossil power growth, with clean power set to meet all
           demand growth in 2023.
                  Analysts projected a 0.3% dip in fossil generation this year, with steeper falls
           expected in subsequent years, as wind and solar deployment accelerate.
                  The International Energy Agency said last year that the electricity sector needs
           to move from being the highest-emitting sector to being the first sector to reach net

           zero by 2040 — if the global economy is to decarbonize by the middle of the century.
                  For this to happen, analysts at Ember said, wind and solar must account for 41%
           of the global power mix by 2030 — a sharp rise from the 12% observed in 2022.
                  Li Shuo, senior policy advisor at Greenpeace East Asia, described China as “the
           800-pound gorilla when it comes to the global power sector.”
                  “This is not only because of China’s sheer scale, but also a concerning trend of

           its electricity sector development. China has no doubt been leading global renewable
           energy  expansion.  But  at  the  same  time, the  country  is  accelerating  coal  project
           approval,” Li said.
                  “This  won’t  carry  the  country  far  to  truly  decarbonize.  Rapid  power  sector
           reforms are needed to put the country back to the carbon neutrality vision it has set
           for itself.”
                  Author: By Sam Meredith, CNBC
           Link:        https://www.nbcnews.com/science/environment/wind-solar-generated-

           record-amount-global-power-2022-rcna79308

           VOCABULARY

            record growth                                   to provide
            renew, renewable                                record, to record
            boom, to boom                                   to emit, emission

            analysis, to analyze                            to increase
            annual electricity                              development, to develop
            demand, to demand                               remain, to remain
            shape, shape, reshape                           sustainment, to sustain
            research, to research                           doubt, to doubt
            to generate

                                                       NOTES

           Ember - formerly known as Sandbag or the Sandbag Climate Campaign, is a non-profit
           organization  that  advocates  for  the  use  of  less  coal.  The  UK-based  organization,
           (found by Bryony Worthington in 2008) was a founder member of The Guardian's
           Environment Network.
                                                         14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[CEO - chief executive officer.

              U.N.  -  is  an  international  organization  created  to  maintain  and  strengthen
              international peace and security, as well as to develop cooperation between states
              and countries.
              International Energy Agency - is an autonomous international institution which aims
              at  working  with  nations  worldwide  to  develop  energy  regulations  for  a  safe  and
              sustainable future. It has 29 participating countries. Formed in Paris in 1974 after the
              oil crisis of 1973-1974.
              Greenpeace East Asia is involved in five key campaigns: water pollution, forests, food

              and agriculture, climate and energy, and air pollution.

              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
              Record growth; wind and solar; worldwide electricity; cleanest-ever level; renewable
              energy;  fossil  age;  fastest-growing  source;  source  of  energy;  annual  electricity
              demand;  wind  generation;  clean  power  era;  meteoric  rise;  rise  to  the  top;  fossil

              emissions; global power demand; electricity transition; accurate picture; Renewables
              and nuclear sources; global energy; new record high; dirtiest fossil fuel; remaining
              gap; chief driver; climate emergency; carbon futures.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              Мировая  экономика;  поэтапный  отказ;  стремительный  подъем;  переход  на
              электроэнергию; данные об электроэнергии; мировой спрос на электроэнергию;
              точная  картина;  крупнейший  источник  энергии;  чрезвычайная  климатическая

              ситуация;  уголь,  нефть  и  газ;  развивающиеся  страны;  устойчивая  энергетика;
              высоко  углеродное  будущее;  солнечная  и  ветровая  энергетика;  мировое
              производство  электроэнергии;  возобновляемые  источники  энергии;  мировая
              экспансия; падение производства ископаемого топлива; быстрые реформы.
                     C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:


              Example:
                                                               Power; life; potency; intensity; efficacy;
               Energy                                          efficiency;  endurance;  spirit;  spirit;
                                                               strength; pluck.


               Fossil


               Pollution



               Carbon

                                                             15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Emission


            Electricity


            Solar



            Renewable




           D. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on pages 12-13. Read the words
           around them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts
           below to make definitions:

            1. Renewable energy                             a. to prevent or reduce the emission of
                                                            carbon gases into the atmosphere as a
                                                            result  of  a  process,  such  as  the
                                                            combustion of fossil fuels:

            2. Fossil fuels                                 b. energy comes from renewable natural
                                                            resources  that  replenish  more  quickly
                                                            than they are consumed.
            3. Decarbonize                                  c.  industry  or  trade  around  the  world
                                                            that  has  developed  as  a  result  of
                                                            globalization
            4. Global economy                               d.  include  coal,  natural  gas,  oil,  and

                                                            nuclear energy.
            5. Subsequent                                   e. happening after something else.


           E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:

               ➢  to meet demand                               ➢  off- track
               ➢  remaining gap                                ➢  subsequent years

               ➢  coal power                                   ➢  climate emergency
               ➢  an accurate picture                          ➢  a sharp increase
               ➢  steep fall                                   ➢  a sheer scale



                                                         16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[TEXT 2


                Amazon creates a new user-centric simulation platform to develop embodied Al
                                                          agents
                     AI-powered  robots  are  generally  trained in  simulation  environments  before
              they  are  tested  and  introduced  in  real-world  settings.  These  environments  allow
              developers to safely test their machine learning techniques on a variety of robots and
              in  numerous  possible  scenarios,  without  having  to  purchase  hardware,  assemble
              robots and then bring them to remote locations, or compromise on real-world safety

              of the deployed systems.
                     Amazon Alexa AI recently  created a new simulation platform specifically  for
              embodied  AI  research,  the  field  specialized  in  the  development  of  autonomous
              robots. This platform, dubbed Alexa Arena, was presented in a paper pre-published
              on arXiv and is publicly available on GitHub.
                     "Our primary objective was to develop an interactive Embodied AI framework

              to catalyze the creation of next-generation embodied AI agents," Govind Thattai, the
              lead scientist for Arena platform, told Tech Xplore. "Several embodied-AI simulation
              platforms have been proposed in recent years (e.g., AI2Thor, Habitat, iGibson). These
              platforms  support  simulated  scenes,  where  embodied  agents  can  navigate  and
              interact with objects, yet most of them are not designed for humans to interact with
              agents due to the lack of user-centricity," said Qiaozi Gao, who co-developed the
              Arena framework.
                     As most available simulation platforms are not user-centric to collect data for

              human-robot interactions, developers often need to conduct real-world experiments,
              which is typically expensive and time consuming. Alternatively, some teams choose
              to develop a so-called "inferencing engine," a computational tool that allows humans
              to directly interact with a simulated environment, yet this also requires time and
              additional research efforts.
                     Embodied agents need to consistently interact with their environments, while
              also learning from and adapting to other agents or humans in a safe and effective

              manner.  While  current  simulation  platforms  focus  on  task  decomposition  and
              navigation, Arena attempts to fill in the missing pieces that would inevitably come
              into play during deployment and real-time evaluation of collaborative robots.
                     Arena is augmented with user-centric features to not only bolster development
              and evaluation of EAI agents, but also to bridge the gap between the development
              and deployment phase. This is done by making humans an indispensable part of the
              EAI development and evaluation process.
                     "To address these challenges, we created Alexa Arena," said Suhaila Shakiah, a

              developer of Arena ML components. "Our platform offers a framework with user-
              centric  capabilities,  such  as  smooth  visuals  during  robot  navigation,  continuous
              background animations and sounds, viewpoints in rooms to simplify room-2-room
              navigation, and visual hints embedded in the scene that aid human-users to generate
                                                             17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[suitable instructions for task-completion. These features enhance usability and user

           experience, enabling human-in-the-loop embodied AI development and evaluation."
                  On  the  Alexa  Arena  platform,  developers  can  develop  and  test  different
           embodied AI agents with multimodal capabilities. These agents can interact with the
           relevant objects or areas in the simulated environment based on the specific requests
           by users, a capability known as visual grounding. They can also learn to follow natural
           language user instructions, which is a vital aspect of human-robot interaction.
                  "Alexa Arena pushes the boundaries of human-robot interaction," explained
           Xiaofeng Gao, an Arena developer. "It offers an interactive, user-centric framework,

           enabling  creating  robotic  tasks  and  missions  that  involve  navigating  multi-room
           simulated environments and real time object manipulation. In a game-like setting,
           users can interact with virtual robots through natural-language dialogue, providing
           invaluable feedback and helping the robots learn and complete their tasks."
                  In contrast with other existing simulation platforms, Alexa Arena has a greatly
           simplified interface for developers and end-users alike. Users can create specific tasks

           and missions for the robots in the simulation environment using in-built hints, and
           features that push the boundaries of human-computer interaction and embodied AI.
           This also helps to collect human-robot interaction data more easily and efficiently,
           while  also  training  robots  to  effectively tackle  interactive  tasks  using  a  variety  of
           different objects and tools.
                  The user-centric platform could soon be used by developers and researchers
           worldwide  to  develop  highly  performing  embodied  AI agents and  smart  robots.
           Meanwhile, the team plans to further enhance Alexa Arena, adding new features and

           simulated scenarios.
                  "We will now continue to improve the Arena platform to support higher and
           better runtime performances, more scenes, a richer collection of objects and a wider
           range of interactions," Govind added. "We will also continue investing in the general
           Embodied AI field, by developing next-generation intelligent robots that can complete
           real-world tasks and engage in natural communication with humans."
           Link:https://techxplore.com/news/2023-04-amazon-user-centric-simulation-

           platform-embodied.html

           VOCABULARY

            simulation environments           to catalyze                    attempt, to attempt
            real-world setting                support, to support            evaluation, to evaluate
            allow                             navigation, to navigate        to bridge
            purchase, to purchase             interaction, to interact       deployment, to deploy

            to assemble                       design, to design              to invest
            remote locations                  collection, to collect         completion, to complete
            deployed systems                  to conduct

                                                         18]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[NOTES

              Amazon - American company, the largest in the world in the markets of e-commerce
              platforms and public cloud computing by revenue and market capitalization.
              AI - the ability of artificial intelligence systems to perform creative functions that are
              traditionally considered the prerogative of human beings.
              Arena - is a new platform for Embodied AI that automates task fulfilment in virtual
              worlds.
              GitHub - the largest web service for hosting IT projects and their joint development.
              Tech Xplore – a website that covers the most recent developments in engineering,

              electronics, and technology.

              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
              AI-powered robots; simulation environments; real-world settings; machine learning
              techniques; possible scenarios; purchase hardware; assemble robots; autonomous
              robots; primary objective; catalyze the creation; lack of user-centricity; human-robot

              interactions;  embodied  agents;  to  fill  in  the  missing  pieces;  real-time  evaluation;
              bolster  development;  an  indispensable  part;  expensive  and  time  consuming;  a
              computational tool; providing invaluable feedback.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              Симуляционная среда; роботы с искусственным интеллектом; предварительно
              опубликованный; перемещаться и взаимодействовать с объектами; восполнить
              недостающие  элементы;  сбор  данных о  взаимодействиях  человека  и  робота;

              повышают  удобство  использования  и  взаимодействие  с  пользователем;
              жизненно  важным  аспектом  взаимодействия  человека  и  робота;  вступать  в
              естественное общение с людьми.

              C. Fill in the table with the opposites of the given words:
                                                               1. to cancel
                                                               2. to distribute
               to assemble                                     3. to disperse
                                                               4. to separate
                                                               5. to scatter


               to catalyze


               to interact



               to deploy

                                                             19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[effectively


            to simplify


            virtual



            intelligent


            artificial



            communication


            contrast



            to engage


            user-centric



           D. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on pages 17-18. Read the words
           around them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts
           below to make definitions:

            1. AI                                          a.methodology        or    approach      that
                                                           consistently identifies user needs.

            2. Computer hardware                           b. real-time


            3. User-centric                                c.Artificial Intelligence is the replication
                                                           of  human  intelligence  functions  by

                                                           machines,        particularly      computer
                                                           systems.



                                                         20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[4. influencing each other                       d. the physical parts of a computer: case,

                                                               central  processing  unit  (CPU),  random
                                                               access  memory  (RAM),  monitor  and
                                                               mouse.
               5.  If  the  process  occurs  at  the  actual
               time, it happens in                             e. interactive






              E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:


                  ➢  collect data for
                  ➢  real time
                  ➢  a computational tool
                  ➢  to require time

                  ➢  vital aspect
                  ➢  natural language
                  ➢  in-built hints
                  ➢  natural communication
                  ➢  a simulated environment










































                                                             21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[UNIT III. ENTERTAINMENT AND CULTURE


                                                       TEXT 1

                                   A ‘Twilight’ television series is in the works

                   CNN — The “Twilight” saga really will live on in eternity.

                   A  television  series  based  on  the  fantasy  romance  novels  by Stephenie
           Meyer is  in  early  development  at  Lionsgate  TV,  a  source  with  knowledge  told
           CNN. The source also said that Meyer is expected to be involved in the series.
                   A Lionsgate spokesperson declined to comment. No other details about
           how the books will be adapted for TV were available.
                   Meyer’s debut “Twilight” novel was published in 2005, followed by the
           “New  Moon,”  “Eclipse”  and  “Breaking  Dawn”  sequels  that  were  published

           through  2008.  More  than 100  million  copies of  the  books  have  been  sold
           worldwide.
                   The series follows Bella  Swan, a human  teenager who moves  to Forks,
           Washington  and  falls  “unconditionally  and  irrevocably”  in  love  with  her  new
           classmate, Edward Cullen.
                   When Bella learns that Edward is in fact a vampire, the story takes twists
           and turns – including a love triangle with werewolf Jacob Black, as well as the
           birth of a vampire-human baby – as the two star-crossed lovers navigate their

           undying commitment to each other.
                   The four books were adapted into a hugely popular five-movie franchise
           that became known as “The Twilight Saga,” which starred Kristen Stewart, Robert
           Pattinson  and  Taylor  Lautner.  The  first  movie  premiered  in  2008  –  turning
           Stewart,  Pattinson  and  Lautner  into  massive  stars  –  and  quickly  drew  in  a
           dedicated and obsessive fan base that became known as “Twihards.”

                   The  movies  combined  went  on  to gross  over  1  billion  dollars,  with
           “Breaking Dawn Part 2” raking in nearly $300 million at the box office since its
           2012 release.
                   Details  on  the  TV  series  at  this  point  are  sparse  but  hold  on,  spider
           monkeys, more on that to come.
           Link:  https://www.cbsnews.com/atlanta/news/a-twilight-television-series-is-in-
           the-works/

           VOCABULARY


            fantasy                                         to follow
            develop, development                            to commit, commitment
            know, knowledge                                 to dedicate, dedication
            expect, expectation                             to combine
                                                         22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[decline, to decline                             point, to point

               comment, to comment                             star, to star
               to adapt                                        release, to release
               to publish                                      sparse

                                                          NOTES
              CNN - CNN is a US television channel headquartered in Atlanta. Founded in 1980
              by American entrepreneur Ted Turner. It is a division of CNN Global owned by
              Warner Bros. discovery. CNN was the first in the world to propose the concept of

              continuous round-the-clock news broadcasting.
              Stephenie Meyer - American writer best known for the Twilight series of novels.
              Lionsgate  TV  -  television  division  of  a  Canadian-American  entertainment
              company.
              The Twilight Saga - is a series of romantic fantasy films based on the Twilight book
              series by Stephenie Meyer.

              Kristen Stewart - American actress. She is best known for her role as Bella Swan
              in the Twilight film series.
              Robert Pattinson - British actor, fashion model and musician. World fame brought
              him the role of Cedric Diggory in the film "Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire"
              and Edward Cullen in the film series "Twilight".
              Taylor  Lautner  -  American  film,  television  and  voice  actor,  singer.  He  is  best
              known for his participation in the films "The Adventures of Sharkboy and Lava",
              "Valentine's Day" and the vampire saga "Twilight", where he played the role of

              Jacob.

              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
              television  series;  fantasy  romance  novels;  early  development;  a  source  with
              knowledge; Meyer is expected to be involved in the series; declined to comment;
              no  other  details;  sequels  that  were  published  through  2008;    more  than  100
              million  copies  of  the  books  have  been  sold  worldwide;  a  human  teenager;

              “unconditionally  and  irrevocably”;    in  love  with  her  new  classmate;  the  story
              takes twists and turns;  love triangle; the birth of a vampire-human baby; books
              were adapted into a hugely popular five-movie franchise;  to gross over 1 billion
              dollars.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              Телесериал,        основанный         на     фантастических         любовных         романах;
              представитель  Lionsgate;  дебютный  роман  Мейер  «Сумерки»  был

              опубликован  в  2005  году;    «Новолуние»,  «Затмение»  и  «Рассвет»;  сериал
              рассказывает  о  Белле  Свон;  история  принимает  неожиданные  повороты;
              «Сумерки. Сага»; премьера первого фильма состоялась в 2008 году, быстро
              привлекла преданных и одержимых фанатов; паукообразные обезьяны.
                                                             23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:

           Example:
                                                            Fanatic;  follower;  devotee;  enthusiast;
            Fan                                             bug; maniac; zealot.

            Movie



            Release


            Premiere



            Sequel


            Franchise


            Star



            Series


           D. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on page 21. Read the words around

           them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts below to
           make definitions:

            1. Sequel                                      a.  a  type  of  film  that  uses  magic  and
                                                           other  supernatural  phenomena  as  a
                                                           primary  element  of  plot,  theme,  or
                                                           setting.
            2. Fantasy film                                b. something that takes place after or as

                                                           a result of an earlier event.
            3. Novel                                       c. the first performance of a musical
                                                           or theatrical work or the first showing
                                                           of a film.






                                                         24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[4. Premiere                                     d.  a fictitious prose narrative  of  book

                                                               length, typically representing character
                                                               and action with some degree of realism.
               5. Franchise                                    e. to sell a person or company the right
                                                               to sell the products and services of your
                                                               company.

              E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:

                  ➢  a fantasy romance
                  ➢  no other details
                  ➢  to be in love with smb
                  ➢  a love triangle
                  ➢  a vital aspect
                  ➢  hugely popular

                  ➢  an undying commitment
                  ➢  obsessive fans
                  ➢  to be involved in smth


                                                          TEXT 2

                             TikTok users are demanding that their favorite musicians
                                                 release sped-up songs


                       Fast songs allow users to fit more of their favorite tunes in their TikTok videos.
                       On TikTok, one of the latest music trends is speeding up popular songs. And
              now,  fans  are  demanding  that  artists  comply  with  their  expectations  for  speedy
              sounds.
                       In one recent controversy, Grammy-winning artist Kim Petras faced backlash

              from her fans after she teased her new song with Nicki Minaj, “Alone.” After she
              revealed a portion of the track that featured a slower beat, some fans revolted.
                       “Mother please change the beat,” said one commenter. “Waittttt I thought I
              was gonna be throwin it this summer, not chillin,” said another. Hundreds of fans
              commented they wanted a faster-paced song.
                       The demands from Petras’ fans are just one part of the sped-up song boom on
              the app.
                       TikTok has seen an increasing number of ‘sped-up’ songs take off in the last

              year, according to a TikTok spokesperson.
                       The hashtag #spedupsounds has amassed 14.8 billion views, and hundreds of
              accounts on TikTok have gained millions of followers from speeding up songs on their
              own and posting them to TikTok.


                                                             25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Artists and labels are now leaning into the trend by releasing their own sped-

           up remixes of songs.
                   The remixes will oftentimes see even more engagement than the original,
           according  to  the  TikTok  spokesperson.  For  example,  In  January,  R&B  star  Miguel
           released an official sped-up version of his 2010 single, “Sure Thing,” which went viral
           on TikTok and made its way into the Billboard Top 20 at #15, over a decade after its
           release.
                   Bad Friends, a dance-pop producer duo based in London, released their own
           version of Petras’ “Alone” just hours after backlash started to mount over the slow

           beat in the most recently released snippet. The duo posted it on their TikTok and
           immediately saw an influx of views and comments. The producers, Noah Tate and
           Hugo  Shaw,  said  they  came  at  their  version  of  the  song  from  their  dance-pop
           background and a genuine love of the sample. Tate and Shaw knew that people would
           want to know what a Minaj verse sounded like on the sample, so they used an AI voice
           splitter website that allows users to isolate vocals from a song, Tate said. They took

           Minaj’s verse from her 2012 song “Whip It” and added it to their version of “Alone.”
           Link:         https://www.nbcnews.com/pop-culture/viral/tiktok-sped-up-fast-songs-
           sounds-rcna79256

           VOCABULARY

            to allow, allowance                             a producer, to produce
            speed, to speed                                 beat, to beat

            to comply                                       background
            boom, to boom                                   a version
            demand, to demand                               a sample, to sample
            an increase, to increase                        use, to use
            a post, to post                                 a splitter, to split
            remix, to remix                                 an isolation, to isolate
            a release, to release                           an addition, to add


                                                       NOTES
           TikTok - service for creating and viewing short videos, owned by the Beijing-based
           company "ByteDance".
           Kim Petras  ( August 27, 1992, Cologne, Germany) - German singer and songwriter.
           Nicki Minaj - Onika Tanya Marage-Petty, known by her stage name Nicki Minaj, is a
           Trinidadian singer, rapper, songwriter and actress.
           AI - branch of computer science that deals with solving cognitive problems normally

           reserved  for  human  intelligence,  such  as  learning,  problem  solving,  and  pattern
           recognition.


                                                         26]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.

              Fast songs; allow users; favorite tunes; TikTok videos; one of the latest music trends;
              is speeding up popular songs; fans are demanding; comply with their expectations for
              speedy  sounds;  in  one  recent  controversy;  faced  backlash;  teased  her  new  song;
              revealed a portion of the track; slower beat; some fans revolted; hundreds of fans
              commented; faster-paced song; sped-up song boom on the app;
              remixes of songs; go viral on TikTok.

              B. Find in the text the English for:

              Миллиарды  просмотров;  сотни  аккаунтов  в  TikTok  получили  миллионы
              подписчиков;  самостоятельно  ускоряя  песни  в  TikTok;  артисты  и  лейблы;
              следуют  этой  тенденции,  выпуская  собственные  ускоренные  ремиксы  песен;
              представитель  TikTok;  ремиксы  часто  привлекают  даже  больше  внимания;
              лондонский продюсерский дуэт танцевальной поп-музыки; негативная реакция;
              увидеть  приток  просмотров  и  комментариев;  искренней  любви;  изолировать

              вокал от песни.

              C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:

              Example:
                                                               Remark;         observation;        opinion;
               comment                                         reflection;  utterance;  pronouncement;
                                                               view; criticism; statement; judgment.


               Song



               Post


               Beat


               Remix



               Trend


               Beat



                                                             27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Sample


           D. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on page 24. Read the words around
           them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts below to
           make definitions:

            1. Trend                                       a. a small part or quantity intended to

                                                           show what the whole is like.

            2. Sample                                      b. a general direction in which
                                                           something is developing or changing.
            3. Post                                        c. sight, perspective, vision, visibility,
                                                           outlook.
            4. Comment                                     d. an opinion, an observation, a
                                                           judgement.

                                                           e. a piece of writing, image, or other
            5. View                                        item of content published online,
                                                           typically on a blog or on social media.

           E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:
              ➢  an increasing number

              ➢  hundreds of fans
              ➢  to comply with one’s expectations
              ➢  to lean into trend
              ➢  to allow users
              ➢  an influx of comments and views
              ➢  most recently
              ➢  to go viral
              ➢  millions of followers























                                                         28]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[UNIT IV. HEALTH AND MEDICINE

                                                          TEXT 1

                   Biden administration proposes tighter health privacy rules around abortion

                       The proposed changes are aimed at strengthening HIPAA protections amid

              concerns medical information could be disclosed to help prosecute abortion care.
                       The  Biden  administration  on  Wednesday  proposed new  health  privacy
              protections to prevent protected health information from being used to investigate
              or sue people who facilitate abortions.
                       The changes, put forth by the Department of Health and Human Services'
              Office for Civil Rights, would bolster reproductive health care privacy.
                       Vice  President  Kamala  Harris  announced  the  new  language,  aimed  at

              strengthening existing privacy rule protections under the Health Insurance Portability
              and  Accountability  Act  of  1996,  during  a  meeting  with  a  task  force  on  access  to
              reproductive health care Wednesday afternoon. She was joined by Attorney General
              Merrick Garland and Health Secretary Xavier Becerra.
                       “We are looking at a situation in our country where health care providers,
              most of whom have had a calling to do the good and important work of taking care of
              other people, are in fear of losing their licenses and worse, even being prosecuted
              and criminalized for the work that they do,” Harris said.

                       She said an exception in HIPAA that allows law enforcement to access medical
              records posed a "real risk of damage to and attacks on patient privacy" in light of
              efforts in some states to criminalize health care providers and others who assist in
              providing abortions.
                       The meeting came after the latest setback to proponents of abortion rights: A
              federal judge in Texas appointed by former President Donald Trump issued a ruling

              last  week  that  would suspend  the  Food  and  Drug  Administration's  longtime
              approval of  the  abortion  drug  mifepristone.  The  Biden  administration filed  a
              request in a federal appeals court Monday to block the ruling.
                       Before speaking about the administration's medical privacy proposal, Harris
              blasted the judge's ruling as "attacking the very credibility of the FDA," with sweeping
              ramifications on the integrity of the country's health care delivery systems.
                       The  HHS  proposal  centers  on  barring  using  or  disclosing  protected  health
              information  that  could  be  used  to  identify,  investigate,  prosecute  or  sue  people,
              health care providers and others involved in seeking or providing abortion care.

              Link:          https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/politics-news/biden-administration-
              propose-tighter-health-privacy-rules-abortion-rcna79257



                                                             29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[VOCABULARY


            a change, to change                             a strength, to strengthen
            a concern, to concern                           criminal, to criminalize
            a proposal, to propose                          a meeting, to meet
            information, to inform                          an access, to access
            an investigation, to investigate                a fear, to fear
            facilitation, to facilitate                     an assistance, to assist
            care, to care                                   an attack, to attack

            aim, to aim                                     a delivery, to deliver
            a privacy                                       an involvement, to involve

                                                       NOTES
           HIPAA  -  Health  Insurance  Portability  and  Accountability  Act  -  Health  Insurance
           Portability and Accountability Act, which was passed on August 21, 1996.

           Biden  -  Joseph Robinette Biden Jr  is  an  American  politician  who  is  the  46th  and
           current president of the United States.
           Kamala Harris - American lawyer and politician, member of the US Democratic Party.
           49th Vice President of the United States since January 20, 2021. First woman, first
           black politician, and first Asian politician to serve as a national vice president in U.S.
           history.
           Donald  Trump  -  American  statesman  and  politician,  entrepreneur,  billionaire  and
           45th President of the United States from January 20, 2017 to January 20, 2021 from

           the Republican Party.

           A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
           To  proposed  changes;  aimed  at  strengthening;  medical  information;  prosecute
           abortion care; The Biden administration; health privacy protections; to sue people
           who facilitate abortions; Department of Health and Human Services' Office for Civil
           Rights; bolster reproductive health care privacy; strengthening existing privacy rule

           protections; access to reproductive health care; federal appeals court;
           block the ruling; sweeping ramifications; delivery systems; abortion care.

           B. Find in the text the English for:
           Закон  об  ответственности  1996  года;  во  время  встречи;  доступ  к
           репродуктивному          здоровью;        министр       здравоохранения;          поставщики
           медицинских  услуг;  потерять  свои  лицензии;  подвергнуться  судебному
           преследованию;  доступ  к  медицинским  записям;  «реальный  риск  нанесения

           ущерба и посягательств на частную жизнь пациентов»;  проведении абортов;
           санитарный  надзор;  апелляционный  суд;    конфиденциальность  медицинских
           услуг;  медицинская помощь в стране; защищенная медицинская информация;
           предоставление услуг по прерыванию беременности.
                                                         30]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:

              Example:
                                                               Charge; protection; control; supervision;
               Care                                            management;           keeping;       charge;
                                                               guidance; attentiveness; charge.


               Credibility


               Health



               Drug


               Abortion


               Patient



               Privacy


               Record



              D. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on pages 27-28. Read the words
              around them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts
              below to make definitions:

               1. A medical record                             a.  termination  of  a  pregnancy  by
                                                               removal  or  expulsion  of  an  embryo  or
                                                               fetus.
               2. Abortion                                     b.  the  practice  of  maintaining  the

                                                               security  and  confidentiality  of  patient
                                                               records.
               3. A medical privacy                            c. an official document from the
                                                               government, court, etc. that gives you
                                                               permission to do, have, or own
                                                               something.


                                                             31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[4. Licence                                     d. a history of someone’s health.

                                                           e. any chemical substance which is given
            5. Drug                                        to people in order to treat or prevent an
                                                           illness or disease.


           E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:
              ➢  a medical record
              ➢  medical privacy
              ➢  health care
              ➢  abortion rights
              ➢  patient privacy

              ➢  health care providers
              ➢  abortion drug mifepristone
              ➢  in the light of smth
              ➢  to sue smb
              ➢  to provide abortion care

                                                       TEXT 2


                    Fungal outbreak at Michigan paper mill suspected to have infected
                                                nearly 100 workers

                  Testing began last month after 15 mill employees became ill with pneumonia-
           like symptoms and revealed they had a fungal infection called blastomycosis.
                  Health officials are investigating nearly 100 suspected cases of a potentially

           severe fungal  infection linked  to  a  Michigan  paper  mill,  nearly  a  month  after
           employees appeared to have "atypical" pneumonia cases.
                  The investigation began in March after 15 employees of the Escanaba Billerud
           Paper Mill appeared to be sick early in the year, Public Health Delta & Menominee
           Counties said in a release at the time. Testing then revealed that the cases were not
           pneumonia but a fungal infection called blastomycosis.
                  At least 19 cases had been confirmed at the paper mill as of Friday, with 74
           more probable cases, the public health department said last week.
                  Blastomycosis  is  caused  by  a  fungus  that  primarily  lives  in  moist  soil  and

           decomposing organic matter, such as wood, and it spreads through the inhalation of
           spores, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Symptoms can
           include fever and cough, and people with more weakened immune systems may have
           more severe cases.
                   The infection can spread to the lungs and other organs, the CDC says.
                   Brian Peterson, the mill's vice president of operations, thanked the local, state

           and federal health agencies assisting in the investigation in a statement Friday.

                                                         32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA["Although the source of the infection has not been established, we continue

              to take this matter very seriously and are following recommendations from health
              and government officials and implementing numerous, proactive steps to protect the
              health and safety of our employees, contractors and visitors," Peterson said.
                       Billerud is a multinational paper and packaging company based in Sweden.
              Link:    https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/fungal-outbreak-michigan-paper-
              mill-suspected-infected-nearly-100-work-rcna79159

              VOCABULARY


               a test, to test                                 to spread
               an employee, to employ                          to implement
               to reveal                                       to appear
               a suspect, to suspect                           to confirm
               an investigation, to investigate                a fungal infection

               a link, to link                                 inhalation, to inhale


                                                          NOTES
              Michigan - is a state in the Midwest of the United States bordered by four Great Lakes.
              It is located on the Lower and Upper Peninsulas, over which more than 11 thousand
              small lakes are scattered. The largest city in the state of Detroit is the world-famous
              center of the country's automotive industry.

              Blastomycosis - is an uncommon, but potentially serious fungal infection. It primarily
              affects the lungs, and is caused by the fungus Blastomyces dermatitidis. The signs and
              symptoms of illness that can result from exposure to this soil organism are variable.
              CDC - The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention is a federal agency of the US
              Department of Health established in 1946 and located in Druid Hills near the Emory
              University campus and northwest of downtown Atlanta.
              Pneumonia - is an inflammatory condition of the lung primarily affecting the small air

              sacs known as alveoli.
              Fungal outbreak - An outbreak occurs when two or more people get sick from contact
              with the same source, sometimes in the same time or place. This can happen outdoors
              or in a health care setting, such as a hospital.

              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
              became  ill  with  pneumonia-like  symptoms;  to  reveal;  a  fungal  infection;  health
              officials;  investigating  nearly  100  suspected  cases;  a  potentially  severe fungal

              infection; "atypical" pneumonia cases; to be sick early in the year; Public Health Delta
              & Menominee Counties; moist soil; decomposing organic matter; to spread through
              the  inhalation  of  spores;  include  fever  and  cough;  people  with  more  weakened
              immune systems; severe cases.
                                                             33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[B. Find in the text the English for:

           заразить  почти  100  рабочих;  15  сотрудников  завода  заболели  симптомами,
           похожими на пневмонию; выявили у них грибковую инфекцию; расследование
           началось  в  марте;  было  подтверждено  не  менее  19  случаев  заболевания,
           министерство  здравоохранения;  центры  по  контролю  и  профилактике
           заболеваний; ослабленная иммунная система;
           инфекция  может  распространиться  на  легкие  и  другие  органы;  местные,
           государственные  и  федеральные  агентства  здравоохранения;  для  защиты
           здоровья и безопасности сотрудников, подрядчиков и посетителей;


           C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
           Example:
                                                            Immunity; antibodies; immune
            Immune System
                                                            response; biosecurity; defense.


            Fungus


            Organic



            Fever


            Symptoms



            Infection


            Cough


            Illness



           D. Find the words in bold in the reading passage on page 30. Read the words around
           them and try to identify their meanings. Then match the sentence parts below to
           make definitions:





                                                         34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[1. Fungus infection                             a.  a  complex  network  of  organs,  cells

                                                               and  proteins  that  defends  the  body
                                                               against  infection, whilst protecting the
                                                               body's own cells.
               2. An immune system                             b.  having  a  temperature  above  the
                                                               normal range.
               3. Fever                                        c. to force air out of your lungs through
                                                               your throat with a short, loud sound,
                                                               often unwillingly.

               4. Cough                                        d. an infection that inflames the air sacs
                                                               in one or both lungs
                                                               e.  include  ringworm,  onychomicosis,
               5. Pneumonia                                    candidiasis,  tinea  versicolor/pityriasis
                                                               versicolor.



              E. Make up sentences using the following phrases and collocations:
                  ➢  a severe case
                  ➢  to be sick
                  ➢  a fungal infection
                  ➢  abortion rights
                  ➢  a weakened immune system

                  ➢  health officials
                  ➢  to protect the health
                  ➢  the source of infection
                  ➢  public health
                  ➢  to have fever and cough































                                                             35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[UNIT V. GENERAL NEWS & CURRENT AFFAIRS


                                                      TEXT 1.A

                             The World Now Needs Green Trade, Not Free Trade

                   Corporations are using trade and investment treaties to handcuff global and

           national efforts to save the planet. That must stop.
                   The global economy hit a new milestone in 2022 by surpassing $100 trillion.
           This expansion, which has experienced only the occasional setback such as the 2020
           COVID  shutdowns,  has  been  accelerated  by  trade.  The  world  trade  volume
           experienced 4,300 percent growth from 1950 to 2021, an average 4 percent increase
           every year. This linked growth of the global economy and international trade took off
           in the 1980s as governments embraced the project of globalization, which prioritized

           the reduction of barriers to trade such as tariffs.
                   The mechanism by which globalization spread throughout the world, the key
           strand of its DNA, has been the “free trade” treaty.
                   “We’ve  had  30  years  of  free  trade  agreements  and  bilateral  investment
           treaties,”  points  out  Luciana  Ghiotto,  a  researcher  at  CONICET-Argentina  and
           associate researcher with the Transnational Institute. “They’ve created this enormous
           legal  architecture,  what  one  friend  of  ours  calls  the  ‘corporate  architecture  of
           impunity,’ which has spread like grass and gives legal security and certainty to capital.

           It has nothing to do with the protection of human rights or environmental rights.”
                   Indeed, among the many problems associated with the expansion of world
           trade  has  been  environmental  degradation  in  the  form  of  land,  air,  and  water
           pollution. More recently, however, attention has turned to the more specific problem
           of carbon emissions, which are largely responsible for climate change. According to
           the World Trade Organization, the production and transport of goods for export and

           import account for 20-30 percent of global carbon emissions.
                   Embedded in many of the treaties governing trade and investment are clauses
           that give corporations the right to sue governments over regulations, particularly
           those  addressing  the  environment  and  climate  change,  that  adversely  affect  the
           expected profit margins of those businesses. These investor-state dispute settlement
           (ISDS)  provisions  have  a  “chilling  effect  on  the  regulatory  system  because
           governments,  worried  that  they  will  be  sued,  decide  to  delay  reforms  related  to
           climate change,” points out Manuel Perez Rocha, an associate fellow of the Institute
           for Policy Studies in Washington. “There have been several cases around the world

           where  companies  were  able  to  defeat  regulatory  changes  that  favor  the
           climate.”Trade rules that privilege corporations over the environment are particularly
           influential in the realm of agriculture, which is an extractive industry no less powerful
           than  mining.    “The  global  system  of  trade  and  investment  contributes  to  the
           monopoly control by just a few transnational corporations over fossil-fuel-guzzling
                                                         36]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[agrobusiness, whose products are often transported thousands of miles before they

              reach a dinner table,” relates Jen Moore, an associate fellow at the Institute for Policy
              Studies. “At the same time the system has been decisive in making the lives of millions
              of small-scale farmers more precarious, undermining their role as a better alternative
              to mass monoculture operations.” Carbon emissions are not the only byproduct of
              the agrobusiness that global trade sustains. “There’s also methane emissions,” adds
              Karen Hansen-Kuhn, program director at the Institute for Agriculture & Trade Policy.
              “A lot of methane comes from meat production. Nitrous oxide, which is 265 times
              more potent than carbon and stays in the atmosphere over 100 years, results from

              chemical fertilizers.”
                            These perspectives on global trade—and more environmentally sound
              alternatives to the “free trade” model—were presented at a December 2022 webinar
              sponsored by Global Just Transition project of the Institute for Policy Studies and the
              Ecosocial and Intercultural Pact of the South.
              Link: https://www.fairobserver.com/more/environment/green-economy/the-world-

              now-needs-green-trade-not-free-trade/

              VOCABULARY

               handcuff                                        decisive
               setback                                         byproduct
               take off                                        to sue
               accelerated                                     regulatory system

               treaty                                          margins
               expansion                                       adversely
               Transnational Institute                         byproduct
               strand                                          settlement
               bilateral                                       undermine
               CONICET                                         favor
               certainty                                       point out

               embedded                                        chilling effect
               extractive                                      nitrous oxide
               fossil-fuel-guzzling                            treat
               small-scale                                     realm
               influential                                     defeat
               emissions                                       relate
               precarious                                      protection
               fertilizers


              Answer the questions:
              1. How much has the global economy surpassed in 2022?
              2. What is responsible for the global economy's expansion?
                                                             37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[3. How much has world trade volume increased from 1950 to 2021?

           4. What was the key strand of DNA for the spread of globalization?
           5. What has been the consequence of the massive legal architecture created by free
           6. What percentage of global carbon emissions is accounted for by the production
           and transport of goods for export and import?
           7. What are ISDS provisions and how do they affect regulatory systems related to
           climate change?
           8. In what industry are trade rules that privilege corporations over the environment
           particularly influential?

           9.  What  are  some  negative  consequences  of  the  global  system  of  trade  and
           investment on small-scale farmers?
           10. What are some environmental consequences of the global agrobusiness sustained
           by trade?
                                                       NOTES
           Green Trade - is trading in companies that focus on improving the environment. It

           aims to speed up the change to a cleaner environment, so it includes sectors such as
           the renewable energy market and energy efficiency.
           Global Just Transition project – will provide updates on the status of Green New
           Deals, ecosocial pacts, and just transition plans around the world.
           The  Institute for Policy Studies - is an American progressive think tank started in 1963
           that is based in Washington, D.C.
           the  World  Trade  Organization (WTO) is an  intergovernmental organization that
           regulates and facilitates international trade. With effective cooperation in the United

           Nations System, governments use the organization to establish, revise, and enforce
           the rules that govern international trade.
           Deoxyribonucleic acid—or DNA— is a  molecule  that  serves  as  the  hereditary
           material  containing  biological  instructions  that  make  every  human  and  other
           organism unique.

           A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.

           Trade; handcuff global; surpassing; accelerated by trade; associate researcher; global
           economy  and  international  trade;  bilateral  investment  treaties;  the  realm  of
           agriculture;  chilling  effect;  human  rights;  human  rights;  byproduct  of  the
           agrobusiness;  small-scale  farmers;  decisive;  mass  monoculture  operations;  an
           extractive industry; the expansion of world trade; adversely affect the expected profit
           margins.

           B. Find in the text the English for:

           торговые и инвестиционные соглашения; глобальные и национальные усилия;
           мировая экономика; расширение; редкие сбои; взаимосвязанный рост мировой
           экономики; соглашение; свободная торговля; защита прав человека; правовая


                                                         38]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[архитектура;  действительно;  транспортировка  товаров;  торговля;  инвестиция;

              младший научный сотрудник; углекислый газ; химическое удобрение.

              C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
              Example:

               Investment                                      capital expenditure;
                                                               investments;
                                                               outlays;

                                                               capital outlay;
                                                               investment cost
                                                               interests;
                                                               investment funds;
                                                               contribution;
                                                               endowment;

                                                               file attachment.

               Mechanism


               Agreement



               Alternative


               Setback



               Effect


               Profit



               Byproduct







                                                             39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[D. Fill in the table with the opposites of the given words:


                                                            1. entertainment
                                                            2. recreation
            Trade                                           3. indolence
                                                            4. idleness
                                                            5. pastime


            Protection

            To spread



            To defeat


            Important


            Extractive



            To expect


            To sue



            To change


            To turn


            Alternative



            To point out





                                                         40]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Canada: Why the country wants to bring in 1.5m immigrants by 2025


                       Canada is betting big on immigration to fill the gap in its economy left by aging
              Baby Boomers leaving the workforce - but not everyone is on board with bringing in
              so many people from abroad. Earlier this month, the federal government announced
              an aggressive plan to take in 500,000 immigrants a year by 2025, with almost 1.5
              million new immigrants coming to the country over the next three years.
                       This  plan  would  see  Canada  welcome  about  eight-times  the  number  of
              permanent residents each year - per population - than the UK, and four-times more

              than its southern neighbour, the United States. But a recent poll shows that there is
              also anxiety about welcoming in so many newcomers.
                       Canada bets big
                       For many years, Canada has tried to attract permanent residents  - landed
              immigrants who have the right to stay in the country indefinitely but who are not
              citizens - to keep the population and the economy growing. Last year, the country

              took in 405,000 permanent residents - the most in its entire history. The reasons are
              in, some ways, about simple math. Like many western nations, Canada has an aging
              population with a lower birth rate. What that means is that if the country wants to
              grow, instead of shrink, it will have to bring in immigrants.
                       Immigration already accounts for practically all of the country's labour force
              growth, and by 2032, it is expected to account for all of the country's population
              growth  too,  according  to  a  government  news  release.  Earlier  this  month,  the
              government announced that by 2025, they hope to bring in 500,000 new immigrants

              a year, up about 25% from 2021 numbers.
                       A unique place in the world
                       Today,  about  one  in  four  Canadians  have  come  to  the  country  as  an
              immigrant, the highest among G7 nations. Compare that to the US, known colloquially
              as the world's melting pot, where only 14% are an immigrant.
                       The UK also has an immigrant population of about 14%. Madeleine Sumption,
              director of the Migration Observatory at Oxford University, said these numbers do

              not mean the UK is behind in immigration, but rather than Canada is a bit of an
              "outlier".
                       The UK, a small island with twice the population of Canada, already has high
              population density, while Canada, which has a population of just over 38 million and
              one of the largest land masses in the world, has room to grow.
                       "Generally the UK has not had an objective of increasing population in the
              same way that Canada (has) done," she said.
                       Geoffrey Cameron, a political scientist at McMaster University, said that while

              many  countries,  like  Canada,  face  lower  birth  rates  and  an aging population,  the
              success of any immigration system relies on popular support.
                       "The limiting factor for most countries is public opinion," he said.


                                                             41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[In the US, where the number of migrants entering the country through the

           southern border has reached an all-time high, there is overall a concern about having
           more immigrants than there are jobs.Pre-Brexit, a wave of European Union migrants
           from eastern Europe moving to the UK created a backlash against migration. But over
           the past several years, Ms Sumption said, popular opinion for immigration has risen,
           in part because people believe the country has better control over who comes in than
           they did before.
                   Canada, meanwhile, has historically had very high support for immigration.
                   "I think part of the reason for that is that there is a degree of public trust that

           immigration to Canada is well-managed by the government and also is managed in a
           way that serves Canada's interests," Mr Cameron said. But that does not mean that
           there are no immigration concerns. In recent years, an influx of migrants at the US
           border has caused some controversy, and the emergence of a new fringe right-wing
           party  in  2018,  the  People's  Party  of  Canada,  kept  the  topic  in  the  national
           conversation in the lead-up to the 2019 federal election.

                   Can Canada meet its targets?
                   Not only does Canada take in more economic-class immigrants than other
           major nations, the country is also one of the top for refugee resettlement, accepting
           20,428 refugees in 2021. But while the country has set ambitious targets for the
           future, history has shown it does not always meet its own expectations. In 2021,
           Canada had a target of resettling about 59,000 refugees - almost three times as many
           as the country took in.
                   In an interview with the CBC, immigration minister Sean Fraser said the gap

           was  largely due  to Covid-related border  closures both  in  Canada  and  around  the
           globe.
                   By 2023, Canada aims to help resettle 76,000 refugees.
           Link: Canada: Why the country wants to bring in 1.5m immigrants by 2025 - BBC News

           VOCABULARY


            workforce                                       European Union
            to bring                                        refugee
            permanent                                       resettlement
            recent                                          concern
            poll shows                                      lead-up
            anxiety                                         backlash
            newcomer                                        meanwhile
            birth rate                                      border closures

            release                                         controversy
            shrink                                          influx
            account                                         colloquially
            Pre-Brexit                                      entire history
                                                         42]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[1. What is the Canadian government's plan for immigration by 2025?

              a) Take in 1.5 million new immigrants over the next five years
              b) Take in 500,000 immigrants every year until 2025
              c) Reduce immigration numbers over the next three years
              d) Take in four times more immigrants than the UK by 2025
              2. Why does Canada need to attract immigrants?
              a) To maintain its labor force growth
              b) To increase fertility rates
              c) To decrease its population density

              d) To compete with other G7 nations
              3. How does Canada's immigration rate compare to that of the UK and the US?
              a) Canada takes in less immigrants than both nations
              b) The UK takes in more immigrants than Canada, while the US takes in less
              c) Canada takes in more immigrants than both nations
              d) The UK and US take in more immigrants than Canada

              4. What makes Canada unique among the G7 nations in terms of immigration?
              a) Its immigration rate is significantly higher than other G7 nations
              b) An overwhelming majority of its population are immigrants
              c) It has the largest land mass in the world
              d) Its immigration system relies on popular support
              5. Why is Canada relying on immigration to grow its population?
              a) Its birth rate is decreasing
              b) Its population density is already high

              c) It wants to compete with other G7 nations
              d) Its economy is shrinking
              6. What is the percentage of immigrants in the US population?
              a) 14%
              b) 25%
              c) 38%
              d) 50%

              7. What is the main reason for the US' concerns about immigration?
              A) The fear of losing political power to immigrants
              B) The fear of having more immigrants than available jobs
              C) The fear of increased crime rates
              D) The fear of cultural assimilation
               8. Why did Canada not meet its target of resettling 59,000 refugees in 2021?
              A) A decrease in the number of refugees seeking resettlement
              B) Lack of funding from the government

              C) A decrease in public support for immigration
              D) Border closures due to Covid-19
              9. Why does Canada historically have high support for immigration?
              A) Due to the country's high population density
                                                             43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[B) Due to public trust in well-managed government policies

           C) Due to the country's large land mass
           D) Due to concerns about border security

                                                       NOTES
           1. Immigrant is an individual who leaves one’s country to settle in another.
           2. Refugees are defined as persons, who move out of one’s country due to restriction
           or danger to their lives.
           3. G7 is a term that is used to describe the "Group of Seven", a coalition of seven

           countries  that  have  the  largest  and  most  advanced  economies  in  the  world:
           the United  States, Germany, Japan,  the United  Kingdom, France, Italy,  and Canada,
           along with the European Union.
           4. CBC is "Canadian Broadcasting Corporation".

           A. Scan the reading passage on pages and answer the questions.


           1. Why does Canada accept immigrants?
           2. What do you know about Canada?
           3. Аre Canadian residents  satisfied with the policy of attracting immigrants?

           B. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
           Baby Boomers; betting big on immigration; workforce; each year - per population;
           instead  of  shrink;  permanent  residents;  public  opinion;  the US  border;  increasing

           population;  set  ambitious  targets  for  the  future;  a  recent  poll  shows;  a  bit  of  an
           "outlier"; border closures; well-managed by the government; an influx of migrants;
           limiting factor; aging population.

           C. Find in the text the English for:
           Большая ставка; заполнить пробел; рабочая сила; федеральное  правительство;
           недавний  опрос;  по  поводу  гостеприимства;  рост  населения  и  экономики;

           неопределенный срок;  пресс-релиз; уникальное место в мире; низкий уровень;
           амбициозные  цели;  закрытия  границ;  в  последние  годы;  наплыв  мигрантов;
           общественное  мнение  в  пользу  иммиграции;  заполнить  пробел;  высокий
           показатель, высокая плотность населения.
               D. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
           Example:
                                                            Transmigration;
            resettlement                                    migration;

                                                            emigration;
                                                            rehousing;
                                                            eviction;


                                                         44]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[relocation;

                                                               settlement.

               Workforce



               Border


               Government



               Support


               Population


               Solution



               Newcomer



              E.Fill in the table with the opposites of the given words:


                                                                   1.  agreement
               controversy                                         2.  accord



               target


               Neighbor


               citizens



               To take

                                                             45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[resident


            To grow


            To give



            to handle


            border



            to meet

















































                                                         46]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[UNIT VI. SPORT & LEISURE


                          TEXT A. How a New York gang truce spawned an Olympic sport

























                 The Rock Steady Crew, seen performing in New York in 1983, were Holman's first
                                             breaking project as a manager

                     The  introduction  of  breaking  into  the  Olympics  for  Paris  2024  may  have
              surprised many, but for Michael Holman - writer, producer, artist, entrepreneur and
              self-dubbed hip-hop pioneer - it was the realization of a 40-year vision. The Games'

              website describes breaking as a "hip-hop" style of dance characterized by 'acrobatic
              movement and stylized footwork'.
                     The format is  fundamentally different to ice dancing or gymnastics  though.
              Athletes don't wait their turn to perform one-by-one and impress judges. Instead
              breakers will take to the floor in pairs in Paris, "battling" head-to-head and upping
              each other's moves to take home a medal.
                     Back in the early 1980s, Holman ran a weekly hip-hop revue in a downtown
              Manhattan club which combined rap and graffiti with the new form of street dance.
                     At first, it was about performance. The breakers would dance, the audience

              would  applaud,  the evening would move  on  and  the  next  act  would  appear. But
              Holman insisted on adding one more element to his booming club night.
                     "New York is all about competition and about trying to be the best," he said.
              "And I wanted to bring another crew along to battle. I want the audience to see a
              battle, not just moves." It's what Holman had witnessed months earlier on the streets
              of the Bronx. There, breaking had emerged as a form of dance combat, springing from

              a shift in the gang tensions that had blighted 1970s New York.
                     "There were the Ghetto Brothers and the Black Spades, the Savage Nomads,
              and the Savage Skulls. And they'd been bloodletting for years: breaking heads, killing,
              stabbing each other," he said.



                                                             47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA["Then, in 1971, Yellow Benjy - the leader of the Ghetto Brothers - forced a truce

           that allowed the guys and gals from rival gangs to get together and party."
                  It  was  at  these  parties,  where  dance  replaced  violence  as  an  outlet  for
           neighborhood bravado, that the city's many cultures cultivated breaking's creativity.
                  Holman continued: "Breakers would watch other breakers saying: 'Wow, that's
           wild. The way you're bringing in Kung Fu moves from the Chinese community. I'm
           going to incorporate your Kung Fu and put it with my African cakewalk dance, or
           incorporate it with a Puerto Rican gymnastics aesthetic.' And all this while dancing to
           old James Brown records mixed on Jamaican-style sound systems. That's the culture

           of b-boy dance."
                  The  first  band  of  breakers  resident  at  Holman's  nights  were  a  group  he
           informally managed called the "Rock Steady Crew". Initially, they were loathed to
           share a stage with a rival outfit, but eventually they relented to Holman's requests.
           "I brought down a crew called the 'Floor Masters' and boom, it was like a historic
           moment," said Holman. "The 'Floor Masters' were much more about athleticism and

           speed and power, and when I saw them battle, I dropped the 'Rock Steady Crew' like
           a hot potato."
                  Holman helped form and then manage a new breaking crew that would focus
           solely on the 'power' moves he'd witnessed from the 'Floor Masters'. They recruited
           the best dancers from the best crews across the city's five boroughs and named the
           new  group  the  'New  York  City  Breakers'.  It  featured  some  of  the  art  form's  best
           exponents:  Noel  'Kid  Nice'  Manguel,  Matthew  'Glide  Master'  Caban,  and  Tony
           'Powerful Pexster' Lopez. Together, they took breaking to an all-new level of skill.

                  "I got rid of the weak dancers and raided three or four other crews from the
           city. I created a super crew of power breaking," said Holman.
                  "The Breakers were able to like, gyroscope. They'd start out doing footwork and
           then go down to the ground and, using some sort of internal propulsion, mixed with
           the friction of the ground, simultaneously ball themselves  up in a certain way or
           spread out in a certain way, they'd create an internal energy. "They were able to spin
           and do these flares. They figured out a new way to move, and it was pure poetry."

                  By the late 1990s, Holman was getting invites to hip-hop conventions all over
           the  world,  with  interest  in Australia,  Asia,  Europe  and  South  America.  He hosted
           panels and lectures about the breaking movement, watched breaking films and took
           part in dance workshops where the original dancers  had been asked  to  make an
           appearance. One young Polish dance crew even made a point of showing him they'd
           learned a routine from Graffiti Rock, move for move. But not all breakers were as
           welcoming.
                  "I used to get a lot of screwy looks from some of the breakers when I showed

           up," said Holman.



                                                         48]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[What will be the break dancing rules at the Olympics?

                       According to the Olympics’ website, breaking will have a men’s and women’s
              competition, with 16 B-Boy finalists and 16 B-Girl finalists. The dancers will compete
              face to face in solo battles. The dancers can combine power moves, such as freezes
              and windmills, and must improvise based on the DJ’s beat. They will be voted on by a
              panel of judges.
              Link: https://www.bbc.com/sport/olympics/64987866

              VOCABULARY


               Olympics                                        propulsion
               Entrepreneur                                    windmills
               self-dubbed                                     flare
               audience                                        simultaneously
               graffiti                                        footwork

               bravado                                         screwy
               competition                                     to spin
               relent                                          recruit
               violence                                        incorporate
               gеt rid of                                      downtown

              Answer the questions:
                  1.  Where will the next Olympic Games be held in 2024?

                  2.  What is the newest game in the Olympics?
                  3.  Do you prefer individual sports or team sports?
                  4.  What are the benefits of doing sport?
                  5.  What was your favorite sport when you were a child?
                  6.  What is Rock Steady Crew known for?

                                                          NOTES

              The Savage Skulls are a mostly Puerto Rican and African American street gang started
              in the Hunts Point area of the Bronx during the late 1960s.
              Rock Steady Crew is an American breaking and hip hop group which has become a
              franchise name for multiple groups in other locations.
              The Chinese  community    is  notable  for  its  austerity,  toughness,  low  profile  and
              business acumen.
              Graffiti is art that is written, painted or drawn on a wall or other  surface, usually
              without permission and within public view.

              B-Boying is a highly expressive dance developed in the Bronx of New York City, USA.
              The cakewalk was  a dance style  of  obscure  origins,  but  is  generally  attributed  to
              African Americans adapting formal European dances.

                                                             49]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
           gang  truce;  spawn;  a  40-year  vision;  the  culture  of  b-boy  dance;  to  make  an
           appearance; springing from a shift in the gang tensions; self-dubbed hip-hop pioneer;
           battle; witness; screwy looks; took part in dance workshops; using some sort of internal
           propulsion; pure poetry; to share a stage with a rival outfit; many cultures cultivated
           breaking's creativity; 'acrobatic movement and stylized footwork; like a hot potato.

           B. Find in the text the English for:

           самопровозглашенного  пионера  хип-хопа,  лицом  к  лицу,  как  форма
           танцевального  боя,  принудил  к  перемирию,  в  эстетику  пуэрториканской
           гимнастики,  исторический  момент,  помог  сформировать,  собрал  команду,
           гораздо  больше  внимания  уделялось  атлетизму,  скорости  и  силе,  приняли
           участие  одни  из  лучших  представителей,  совершенно  новый  уровень
           мастерства, создавали внутреннюю энергию, польская танцевальная команда,

           примут участие 16 финалистов, комбинировать силовые движения.

              D. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
           Example:
                                                            businessperson
            Entrepreneur                                    owner
                                                            business
                                                            enterpriser

                                                            venturer
                                                            private entrepreneur
                                                            employer
                                                            businessman
                                                            businesswoman
                                                            female entrepreneurs


            To spin


            Movement



            Downtown


            Competition



                                                         50]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Spawn


               Violence


               Outfit



              E.Fill in the table with the opposites of the given words:
                                                                   1.  external
               Internal



               Battle


               Combine



               Citizens


               To create



               Footwork


               To spread out


               To take



               Incorporate


               To allow



                                                             51]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Host


        TEXT B. Gheorghe Hagi: Inside a football icon's plan to restore Romania's glory days























           Gheorghe Hagi, 58, remains the most celebrated player in Romanian football history


                  Romania have not qualified for a World Cup since 1998 and have reached the
           European Championships only twice since 2000, failing to get past the group stage on
           both  occasions.  They  begin  their  attempt  to  qualify  for  Euro  2024  with  matches
           against Andorra and Belarus this month.
                  Gheorghe Hagi, who illuminated Romania's run to the World Cup quarter-
           finals of 1994 and is widely regarded as their best player of all time, is on a mission
           to transform their fortunes.
                  "Hagi  for  president"  was  chanted  by  hundreds  of  thousands  back  home  as

           Romania beat Colombia, hosts USA and Argentina on their way to the World Cup
           quarter-finals  in  1994.  Penalty  defeat  by  Sweden  followed,  but  the  wave  of
           unprecedented love towards the nation's football hero lost little momentum.
                  Two  years  later,  despite  Hagi  not  running  in  Romania's  1996  presidential
           elections, people still voted for him.  They wrote his name out by hand, with the
           midfielder getting a few thousand votes, more than some of the official candidates.

                  Over a 29-year professional career that ended at Galatasaray in 2001, Hagi
           played for Real Madrid and Barcelona and appeared 124 times for his country, scoring
           a joint record 35 goals. They called him the 'Maradona of the Carpathians'. He placed
           fourth for the Ballon d'Or in 1994 and Pele included him in a 125-strong list of the
           world's  best living players in 2004. Hagi turned  to management months  after his
           retirement from professional football. His first job? The Romania national team. For
           the 'King', as he is known in Romania, it was a rough start. His side lost to Slovenia in
           the World Cup qualification play-offs and missed out on a place at the tournament for
           the first time since 1986.

                                                         52]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[When he was playing, Hagi could decide everything on his own through an

              unexpected shot, a mazy dribble or a keyhole assist.
                     "I had personality, I had good ball control and I was fast," Hagi says. "I grew up
              with the Netherlands team in the 1970s, with total football. Johan Cruyff was my idol.
              I wore the number 10 most of the time and I knew what that meant: create a goal or
              score.
                     "I wore the number 10 shirt for Real Madrid and Barcelona, two of the best
              teams in the world. My ambition was always to be the best - that was my biggest
              motivation."

                     In management, things seemed more difficult for him. Things did not work out
              so brilliantly at the start - but the picture is different now.
                     Now 58, he is the owner and head coach of Farul Constanța, Romania's current
              top-flight leaders. After jobs at Galatasaray, Bursaspor and Steaua Bucharest, in 2009
              he  returned  to  his  hometown  of  Constanța  on  the  Black  Sea  coast  with  a  bold
              ambition. He started an academy from scratch, investing part of his own fortune and

              borrowing the rest to support the project. More than £10m was injected to fuel his
              dream: creating a generation that would get Romania in the fight to win the World
              Cup.
                     Short presentational grey line Hagi still entertains during training sessions with
              his dribbling skills, free-kick masterclasses and passing abilities. He is the king in his
              castle, with young prospects' faces lighting up as he walks past. When he started the
              academy, more than 200 kids from all around the country joined. About 100 staff
              were hired.

                     The academy took over a third-tier club, Viitorul Constanța, and quickly won
              consecutive promotions to the top flight. In 2017 the almost unthinkable happened -
              Hagi's team won the Romanian title, with cup success following two years later. In
              2021 the club merged with the well-supported Farul Constanța, where Hagi's own
              journey in football began when he was 10 years old.
                     A big part of the money Hagi earned as a player is now invested in his club. Farul
              are one of the youngest teams in Europe, with the club's philosophy centred around

              youth development. Recently, Hagi offered a 14-year-old his top-flight debut.
                     Over the years, teenagers who have impressed have moved abroad, joining
              Ajax,  Fiorentina,  Brighton,  and  Rangers.  Almost  half  of  the  most  recent  Romania
              squad have a background in Hagi's team, while the percentages in the youth national
              sides are even more impressive. One of those who rose through the ranks at the
              academy is  Hagi's  son, Ianis. The 24-year-old is  now at Rangers, after playing for
              Fiorentina and Genk.
                     "A good player can go out and do his job anywhere," Hagi says. "The league

              doesn't matter. Ianis won the award for Rangers' best young player before his knee
              ligament injury (in January 2022), so he adapted fairly well. Bad luck with his injury.
              But if I never got to play in England, maybe he will - why not?


                                                             53]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA["I had two opportunities to play in the Premier League and I'm sorry I finally

           missed both. It's a country I like and respect. I'm sure fans would have enjoyed my
           style."
                  Tottenham and Newcastle tried to sign Hagi in the 1990s. Cruyff and Barcelona
           were in the way in 1994. Then Galatasaray tempted him with a big European project
           close to home two years later.
                  "I loved Kevin Keegan as a kid - he was one of my idols - so I would have loved
           to play under him at Newcastle," Hagi says. "But when Cruyff calls you in person and
           asks you to go with him to Barcelona, it's hard to resist. He said I was his favourite

           number 10.
                  "Then  I  opted  for  Galatasaray.  They  wanted  to  build  a  team  that  would
           challenge for continental success. Also, they were closer to Romania, and I always had
           the idea to return home after football.
                  "I wrote a book. I put everything inside about my tactics, my philosophy, about
           how I see football. You have to start with the basics, do the simple things first, then

           go step by step towards the more complicated. My motto is: I'm born to win, not just
           to exist. So I'm trying to apply that in everything I do and I want to inspire those I work
           with to do the same.
                  "Cruyff is my inspiration. The way he did things was just amazing. I learned so
           much from him, from his methods and ideas."
                  Hagi's academy aims to promote at least two players to the first team each
           season. The manager doesn't care about the age of those he trains.
                  "I was lucky enough to have good teachers who accelerated my progress. That's

           what I want to do myself," he adds.
                  "This entire academy is my way of giving something back to football because I
           always felt indebted."
                  The  academy  lies  just  outside  Constanța,  a  city  of  about  300,000  people
           situated on the Black Sea coast. Before Hagi's project came to this location it was a
           field where local farmers used to graze their cows and sheep.
                  Hagi was promised a new stadium would be built in Constanța, able to hold

           20,000  -  four  times  the  capacity  of  the  ground  the  team  currently  occupy  at  his
           academy. The Romanian government will invest almost £100 million into the new
           project, which should be ready by 2025.
                  "I returned to Constanța because it's where I was born," Hagi says. "This is my
           place - Farul made me.
                  "I am working to create champions. I want to create world champions. I believe
           in this. I believe in the work I'm doing and in the talent of the Romanian players.
                  "You need to set the biggest goals and believe tirelessly. Otherwise, you aren't

           going to do much."
                  Link: https://www.bbc.com/sport/football/64920773


                                                         54]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[VOCABULARY


                      attempt                                         qualification
                      to qualify                                      play-offs
                      unprecedented                                   scratch
                      staff                                           squad
                      situated                                        midfielder
                      location                                        rough
                      to graze                                        miss out

                      tirelessly                                      impressive
                      to exist                                        to fuel
                      coast                                           management
                      field                                           retirement
                      centred                                         dribble
                      inspiration                                     keyhole

                      percentage                                      assist
                      occasion


                                                              NOTES
                     European Championship, formally UEFA European Championship, also called
              Euro,  in  football  (soccer),  a  quadrennial  tournament  held  between  the  member
              countries of the Union of European Football Associations (UEFA).

                     World Cup,  formally  FIFA World Cup,  in  football  (soccer),  quadrennial
              tournament of men’s national teams that determines the sport’s world champion.
                     Constanța is one of the warmest cities in Romania. It has a humid continental
              climate with oceanic and semi-arid influences.
                     Galatasaray is a Turkish professional football club from Istanbul, part of the
              Galatasaray  Sports  Society  and  competing  in  the  Turkish  Championship.  It  was
              founded in 1905.

                     Johan Cruyff is widely regarded as a legend in football.  After his retirement
              from  playing  and  coaching  Johan  Cruyff  initiated  the  Cruyff  Foundation,  Cruyff
              Institute, Cruyff Classics, Cruyff Football and Cruyff Library.

              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult the dictionary if necessary.
                     The European Championships; widely regarded; the wave of unprecedented
              love;  Penalty  defeat  by  Sweden  followed;  he  started  an  academy  from  scratch;
              presidential elections; after his retirement from professional football; a rough start; a

              mazy dribble or a keyhole assist; create a goal or score; top-flight debut; the youth
              national sides; entire academy; the team currently occupy at his academy; invest
              almost £100 million; believe tirelessly; unthinkable happened.

                                                             55]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[B. Find in the text the English for:

                  пройти  групповой  этап;  дойти  до  четвертьфинала  чемпионата  мира;
           считается  лучшим  игроком  команды  всех  времен;  скандировали  сотни  тысяч
           людей у себя дома; полузащитник; официальные кандидаты; забив рекордные
           35  мячей;  Сборная  Румынии;  тяжелое  начало;  плей-офф  квалификации
           чемпионата мира; забить гол или забить голкиперу; oн основал академию с нуля;
           вложено в реализацию его мечты; поднялся по служебной лестнице в академии;
           ускорили мой прогресс.


           C. Give the synonyms and complete the list:
           Example:
                                                            prepare
            Qualify                                         modify
                                                            specify
                                                            classify

                                                            characterize
                                                            categorize
                                                            characterize
                                                            restrict
                                                            certify


            Attempt



            Fortune


            To promote


            Field


            Location



            Retirement


            Scratch



                                                         56]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[D. Fill in the table with the opposites of the given words:


                                                               1. to build
                                                               2. to conquest
               To defeat                                       3. to attract
                                                               4. to fail
                                                               5. to help


               management


               to graze



               to exist


               fuel


               occasion



               To occupy


               Rough



               to inspire


               to create



                                       True or false Football quiz questions
                 1.  It took Cristiano Ronaldo 27 games to score his first Champions League goal
                 2.  The phrase 'park the bus' arose when Jose Mourinho was forced to park the
                     Chelsea team bus after the bus driver fell ill.
                 3.  Singer in Irish boyband Westlife Nicky Byrne played for Leeds United before
                     moving into music.


                                                             57]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[4.  Sir Alex Ferguson managed the Scotland national team.

              5.  Liverpool legend Kenny Dalglish is known as 'King Kenny' because he is related
                  to the British Royal Family.
              6.  Frank Lampard has scored more Premier League goals than Thierry Henry,
                  Robbie Fowler and Michael Owen.
              7.  Bayern Munich star Thomas Muller is a keen chess player and once won a
                  Bavarian chess tournament.
              8.  Former Brazil and Barcelona star Ronaldinho spent time in prison after being
                  found to have used a fake passport.

              9.  David Beckham took ballet lessons during his time at Manchester United in
                  order to improve his agility.
              10. Brazil icon Pele once starred in a Hollywood movie alongside Michael Caine
                  and Sylvester Stallone.




























































                                                         58]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[UNIT VII. LIFESTYLE


              TEXT 1A. The teenager who made medical history to save her mother

















                  Aliana Deveza organised the organ swap which saved her mum, Erosalyn's, life

                     When she was just  19, Aliana Deveza organised  and underwent  an historic
              operation to save her mum's life. She persuaded a hospital to do the first organ swap

              in the United States where different organs were exchanged between unrelated pairs
              of donors.
                     "The first thing that I asked when I woke up was just how was my Mom? Is she
              okay? Did she make it?
                     "I wasn't really worried about myself anymore, I was just kind of focused on
              getting through the pain that I was feeling. Just hearing that everybody had made it,

              I was able breathe again."
                     When Aliana says everyone else, she's not just talking about herself and her
              mother, because two other women - sisters - were also having operations. One of
              Aliana's organs would go to one of the sister, and one of the sister's kidneys would go
              to Aliana's mum. Two lives were being, with two people donating organs to strangers
              to save a family member. The operation was the result of two years of hard work
              which paid off. Aliana had saved her mother Erosalyn from years of kidney dialysis,
              illness and possibly an early death -and a complete stranger would go on to live a new

              life. Kidneys are one of the only organs a living person can donate to another, as most
              of us are born with two but we only need one to function. Yet people who need a
              kidney are not always able to take one from someone they love, even if that person
              is willing to give it. Across the world around 150,000 organs were transplanted in 2019
              - a small fraction of those who need a new organ. Alvin Roth shared the prize for
              Economics from the Nobel Foundation in 2012 for his work devising a system to help
              more people give and get kidneys.

                     "Unlike many organs its possible for someone to give a kidney to someone they
              love and save their life," he explains.
                     "But sometimes they can't take your kidney even though you're healthy enough
              to give one. And perhaps I'm the donor in a in a similar pair, I would love to give a

                                                             59]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[kidney to someone I love but I can't.

                  "But maybe my kidney would work for your patient and your kidney would work
           for my patient. That's the simplest kind of kidney exchange where two donor pairs
           get together, and each one gets a compatible kidney from the other patients."
           The work of Alvin Roth and his colleagues resulted in a system which has been able to
           scale up the number of kidney swaps, so now each year thousands of lives are saved.
           But these organ exchanges are not yet legal everywhere. In Germany, for example,
           you can still only give an organ directly to someone in your immediate family. One
           concern is that vulnerable people will be tempted to sell an organ for money. It's not

           pairs of people. In some cases chains of people have come together to maximise the
           number of matched kidneys.
                  In one case, 70 different people were brought together so 35 donors gave
           their kidneys to 35 strangers so that others could get a new lease of life.
                  Aliana wasn't able to swap her kidney with her mother because doctors feared
           the  kidney  problems  her  mum  had  might  be  hereditary,  so  Aliana  might  have  it

           too.She still wanted to help her mum get a new kidney but time was running out, so
           she started to do some research and found it might be possible to swap part of a liver
           for a kidney.
                  "I started researching, the type of organs that can be donated while a person
           was still alive. And the liver is what came up most." Aliana did not know that this was
           just  a  theoretical  possibility  and  was  not  a  regular  operation.  She  started  calling
           hospitals to see if she could donate part of her liver to someone in exchange for a
           kidney for her mum. Aliana says a few hospitals did not understand what she meant:

           "I had a few hospitals transfer me to the morgue, because they didn't know what I
           was talking about." Eventually she did get the right person for the job. John Roberts a
           surgeon at the University of California in San Francisco.
                  "He didn't just brush it off. I mean, I was just this 19-year-old girl, and I didn't
           know if I sounded crazy. My family was against it because they didn't want me putting
           myself in any danger." With the help of the hospital they found two sisters who would
           pair with Aliana and her mum. One of the sisters would get part of Aliana's liver, and

           Aliana's mum would get a new kidney from the other sister.Aliana has no regrets, so
           why does she think more of us are not doing it? "I think people gravitate away from
           the idea of organ donation, because of the fear surrounding it.
                  "These  are  major  operations,  there  are  definitely  a  lot  of  risks,  but
           understanding it and going through the process with a team that will be there for you
           during the process is what helps."









                                                         60]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[VOCABULARY


                      swap                                            exchange
                      gravitate                                       dialysis
                      donate, donation                                run out
                      kidney                                          fear
                      regret                                          surround
                      eventually                                      alive
                      transfer                                        exchange

                      surgeon                                         vulnerable
                      liver                                           unrelated

                     Quiz questions

                     1) Why is Aliana Deveza significant in the medical community?

                     A. She was the first kidney donor in the United States.
                     B. She organised and underwent the first successful organ swap in the United
              States.
                     C. She convinced doctors to start using a new medicine.
                     D. She was the first person to receive a kidney transplant from a stranger.

                     2) Why can kidneys be donated by living donors?
                     A. Most people are born with more than one kidney.

                     B. Living donors can donate any organ they choose.
                     C. Kidneys are the only organs that can be donated while the donor is alive.
                     D. Kidneys do not function properly in all people.

                     3) What is the outcome of Alvin Roth's work?
                     A. Thousands of lives have been saved through increased kidney exchanges.
                     B. The sale of organs has been regulated worldwide.

                     C. The number of organ transplants has decreased in recent years.
                     D. Kidney donors are no longer needed because of Roth's work.

                     4) Why aren't organ exchanges legal everywhere?
                     A. Organ exchanges are dangerous and can result in the death of the donor.
                     B. Vulnerable people may be tempted to sell their organs for money.
                     C. Organ exchanges are too expensive to be practical.
                     D. There is a shortage of people willing to donate organs.


                     5) What motivated Aliana to donate part of her liver for her mother?
                     a)  Her  mother’s  kidney  problems  were  hereditary,  and  doctors  refused  to
              perform a kidney transplant between them.
                                                             61]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[b)  Aliana  wanted  to  help  her  mother  get  a  new  kidney,  even  if  it  meant

           endangering her own life.
                  c) Aliana learned through her research that it was possible to donate part of
           her liver for a kidney in exchange.
                  d) None of the above.

                  6)  Why  did  Aliana  face  difficulty  reaching  out  to  hospitals  for  the  organ
           exchange?
                  a) She was calling the wrong hospitals.

                  b) She didn't know how to explain the process of organ exchange.
                  c) Some hospitals didn't believe in organ exchange.
                  d) All of the above.

                  7) Why do some people hesitate to become organ donors?
                  a) They are afraid of the risks involved in organ donation.

                  b) They don't believe in organ donation as a viable medical solution.
                  c) They are not aware of the process of organ donation.
                  d) None of the above.


                           TEXT 1B. Would you give 10% of your salary to charity?



















                     John Yan says he wanted to help people less fortunate than himself

                  John Yan has decided to start giving away at least 15% of his annual salary,

           despite it meaning that he'll have to work longer into his old age. The 27-year-old
           software engineer began donating part of his wages in 2019, pledging 1% that year,
           before raising it to 3% in 2020, and then a big jump to 15% in 2021.
                  "In practical terms this commitment means I'm not going to retire early," says
           Mr Yan, who lives and works in New York City. "And may be looking ahead, I won't be
           able to send my kids to private [fee-paying] school." He is donating the money via a
           global scheme called Giving What We Can (GWWC). This encourages people to sign


                                                         62]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[up as a member and pledge to give 10% of their earnings to charity. Members can

              either donate directly to a charity of their choosing, or pick from a list that GWWC
              recommends. The later includes some funds run by the initiative's parent charity -
              Centre For Effective Altruism - which is registered in both the UK and the US. Mr Yan,
              who is the child of first-generation immigrants to the US, says he knows that he is
              "doing better than a lot of people in the world" and wanted to give something back -
              to help others.
                     "I realised it could only cost a small amount of my happiness to give a greater
              amount to other people," he says.

                     GWWC was founded in 2009 by two Oxford university students - Will MacAskill
              and Toby Ord. Both are now philosophy academics who focus on "effective altruism",
              which explores the most effective ways to help others.
                     It is claimed that 6,439 people around the world have now signed up, with more
              than  $244m  (£183m)  donated  so  far.  Members  record  their  donations  on  the
              scheme's website. And while the pledge is designed to be a lifetime one, people can

              drop out if their circumstances change.
                     Far from the pandemic slowing down the number of people signing up, GWWC
              says that it saw its fastest-ever growth in 2020. More than 1,000 new members signed
              up last year, as Covid and lockdowns made many of us think more about others and
              a bigger world picture.
                     A further 1,000 people are said to have made one off donations via GWWC in
              2020, or agreed to give less than 10% over a more limited timeframe.
              But why encourage people to give away 10% of their income rather a than higher or

              lower level?
                     "The  amount  was  chosen  because  it  strikes  a  good  balance  of  being  both
              significant and sustainable," says GWWC executive director Luke Freeman. "It is a
              significant proportion of one's income, but it is also within reach of most people in
              rich countries."
                     He also points to the historical connection of the idea of tithing, a tradition in
              both Judaism and Christianity of giving 10% of your income to charity or the church.

              The 10% pledge is a minimum, and some members, such as Mr Yan, decide to give a
              higher amount.
              Pippa Gilbert started donating 10% of her income to GWWC a few years ago.
                     "I had much more than I needed to live on, and much of the world doesn't, so
              it seemed obvious to me," says the 60-year-old who is from The Hague, Netherlands.
                     This  year  Ms  Gilbert  retired  from  her  job  as  analyst  for  an  international
              organisation  meaning  her  income  has  fallen.  "But  it's  still  more  than  I  need
              personally," she says. While those signing up include students, retirees, trades people

              and investment bankers, Mr Freeman says that there is a skew towards people on
              middle to higher incomes and those with higher education levels - the median age of
              members is about 30.


                                                             63]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA["While  many  on  lower  incomes  find  great  meaning  in  their  giving,  we  do

           particularly encourage those who have more to give more," says Mr Freeman.
                  Boston-based couple Julia Wise and Jeff Kaufman are two high earners who are
           now donating 50% of the combined salary to charities - mainly, Against Malaria Fund
           and Malaria Consortium. They do this via a non-profit organisation called Givewell,
           which researches charities to establish which ones are the most effective.
                  "I felt from an early age that we should be sharing in some way to make the
           world a better and fairer place," says Ms Wise, 36.
                  However, GWWC, and the wider effective altruism movement, are not without

           their  critics.  These  say  that  such  charitable  donations  should  never  be  seen  as  a
           substitute to a decent level of taxation and state social services.
                  However, GWWC, and the wider effective altruism movement, are not without
           their  critics.  These  say  that  such  charitable  donations  should  never  be  seen  as  a
           substitute to a decent level of taxation and state social services.
                  "It's great that people are giving more money to charity, but this cannot be a

           substitute for an adequate social security safety net funded by higher taxes," says
           economist Jeevun Sandher from King's College London.
                  "US citizens consistently give more to charity than those of any other nation (a
           record $471bn in 2020) yet the US also has the second-highest poverty rate in the
           OECD - this is not a coincidence. There are three reasons why charitable giving cannot
           be a substitute for a well-funded welfare state. Firstly, the amounts given in charitable
           donations simply do not make up for a well-funded welfare state.
                  "Secondly, giving low-income people cash is the most reliable way to help pull

           them out of poverty. Charities that provide food, classes and youth centres for those
           on low-incomes do improve lives, but they cannot replace cold, hard cash.
                  Finally, charitable giving is not a reliable source of income, nor is it available to
           everyone on low-incomes."
                  Jennifer Rubenstein, assistant professor of politics at the University of Virginia,
           and author of Between Samaritans and States, adds that effective altruism "does not
           empower poor people as political actors or entities".

                  Mr Freeman counters that charities still play a vital role in helping to tackle
           extreme poverty around the world.
                  "Many of us are wealthier than we think, and many of us can make effective
           giving a meaningful part of our lives," he says. "A median income in countries like the
           UK puts you comfortably within the top 5% richest people in the world.
                  "That money can improve the life of someone in extreme poverty by about 100
           times more than it can improve your own life."
                  Additional reporting by New Economy series editor Will Smale.


           Link: Would you give 10% of your salary to charity? - BBC News


                                                         64]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[VOCABULARY


               lockdown                                        low-income
               annual                                          welfare
               comfortably                                     taxation
               tackle                                          executive
               poverty                                         drop out
               entity                                          circumstance
               charity                                         scheme

               altruism                                        timeframe
               empower

                                                          NOTES
              GWWC (Giving What We Can) - a global scheme that encourages people to donate
              10% of their earnings to charity.

              The  OECD  (the  Organisation  for  Economic  Co-operation  and  Development)  is  an
              international organisation that works to build better policies for better lives.
              GiveWell is an independent nonprofit focused on helping people do as much good as
              possible with their donations.
              Software  engineers  are  computer  science  professionals  who  use  knowledge  of
              engineering  principles  and  programming  languages  to  build  software  products,
              develop computer games, and run network control systems.


              Quiz questions
              1. What made John Yan decide to donate 15% of his annual salary?
              A. He wanted to retire early.
              B. He wanted to send his kids to private school.
              C. He knows he is doing better than a lot of people in the world and wanted to help
              others.
              D. His company required him to donate a percentage of his salary.


              2. What is Giving What We Can (GWWC)?
              A. A charity that helps people pay their bills.
              B. A global scheme that encourages people to donate 10% of their earnings to
              charity.
              C. A car rental company that gives a portion of their earnings to charity.
              D. An initiative that helps people start their own charity.


              3. Why was the amount of 10% chosen by GWWC as the recommended donation
              level?
              A. It is the minimum amount required by the government.
              B. It is the maximum amount that people can donate.
                                                             65]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[C. It strikes a good balance of being both significant and sustainable.

           D. It is the only amount that GWWC recommends.

           4. How has the pandemic affected the number of people signing up for GWWC?
           A. The number of people signing up has decreased.
           B. The number of people signing up has remained the same.
           C. The number of people signing up has increased slightly.
           D. The number of people signing up has increased significantly.
           5. What is the historical connection between Judaism and Christianity regarding

           charitable giving?
           A. Both religions require members to donate a certain percentage of their income to
           charity or the church.
           B. Judaism requires members to donate 10% of their income to charity or the
           church, while Christianity does not have a specific requirement.
           C. Christianity requires members to donate 10% of their income to charity or the

           church, while Judaism does not have a specific requirement.
           D. Neither religion has a history of charitable giving.

           6. Why did Pippa Gilbert start donating 10% of her income to GWWC?
           A. She believed it was a requirement of her religion.
           B. She had more than she needed and wanted to give back to those who have less.
           C. She was pressured by friends and family to donate.
           D. She wanted to get a tax deduction.


           7. What is the demographic of GiveWell members and why does Will Freeman
           encourage those who have more to give more?
           A. The median age of members is about 30, and they are primarily students,
           retirees, trades people, and investment bankers. Freeman encourages those who
           have more to give more to help offset the cost of running GiveWell.
           B. The median age of members is about 30, and they are primarily middle to higher

           income earners with higher education levels. Freeman encourages those who have
           more to give more because they are capable of making a bigger impact.
           C. The median age of members is about 50, and they are primarily low-income
           earners. Freeman encourages those who have more to give more to help offset the
           cost of running GiveWell.
           D. The median age of members is about 30, and they are primarily unemployed.
           Freeman encourages those who have more to give more to help support those who
           are unable to donate.


           8. What is economist Jeevun Sandher's argument against charitable donations and
           what is his proposed solution to poverty?
           A. Sandher argues that charitable donations are a substitute for a well-funded
                                                         66]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[welfare state and proposes that low-income people should be given cash.

              B. Sandher argues that charitable donations do not make a difference in poverty
              levels and proposes that higher taxes should be imposed to fund a well-funded
              welfare state.
              C. Sandher argues that charitable donations are important but cannot replace a
              well-funded welfare state and proposes that charities should work together with the
              government to provide social services.
              D. Sandher argues that charitable donations are unnecessary and proposes that the
              government should not provide social services to the impoverished.




































































                                                             67]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[UNIT VIII. MULTICULTURAL PRESS


                                                      TEXT 8A

                          Diverse Teams Feel Less Comfortable — and That’s Why
                                               They Perform Better


                  In  numerous  studies,  diversity  —  both  inherent  (e.g.,  race,  gender)  and
           acquired (experience, cultural background) — is associated with business success. For
           example,  a  2009  analysis  of  506  companies  found  that  firms  with  more  racial  or
           gender diversity had more sales revenue, more customers, and greater profits. A 2016
           analysis of more than 20,000 firms in 91 countries found that companies with more
           female  executives  were  more  profitable.  In  a  2011  study  management  teams
           exhibiting  a  wider  range  of  educational  and  work  backgrounds  produced  more-

           innovative products. These are mere correlations, but laboratory experiments have
           also shown the direct effect of diversity on team performance. In a 2006 study of
           mock juries, for example, when black people were added to the jury, white jurors
           processed the case facts more carefully and deliberated more effectively.
                  Under  increasing  scrutiny,  and  mindful  of  the  benefits  of  diversity  on  the
           bottom  line,  many  companies  are  trying  to  recruit  and  retain  a  more  diverse
           workforce. Success has so far been marginal. With so much at stake, why aren’t these
           companies making more headway? One reason could be that, despite the evidence

           about their results, homogenous teams just feel more effective. In addition, people
           believe that diverse teams breed greater conflict than they actually do. Bringing these
           biases to light may enable ways to combat them.
                  Homogenous Teams Feel Easier — but Easy Is Bad for Performance
                  A  revealing  2009  study  of  fraternity  and  sorority  members  published  in
           Personality  and  Social  Psychology  Bulletin  offers  a  remarkable  window  into  the

           workings  of  diverse  and  homogenous  teams.  Fraternity  and  sorority  membership
           conveys  a  powerful  group  identity,  much  like  political  or  religious  affiliation,  and
           consequently can create a strong sense of similarity (or dissimilarity) with others. In
           the experiment, teams were asked to solve a murder mystery. First, students were
           individually given 20 minutes to study the clues and pinpoint the likely suspect. Next,
           they were placed into teams of three with fellow members from the same Greek
           house and given 20 minutes to discuss the case together and provide a joint answer.
           Five  minutes  into  the  discussion,  however,  they  were  joined  by  a  fourth  team
           member, someone from either their own house or another one.

                  After collectively naming their suspect, members individually rated aspects of
           the discussion. More diverse groups — those joined by someone from outside their
           own fraternity or sorority — judged the team interactions to be less effective than did
           groups joined by insiders. They were also less confident in their final decisions.


                                                         68]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[Intuitively,  this  makes  sense:  On  a  homogenous  team,  people  readily

              understand  each  other  and  collaboration  flows  smoothly,  giving  the  sensation  of
              progress. Dealing with outsiders causes friction, which feels counterproductive.
                     But in this case their judgments were starkly wrong. Among groups where all
              three original members didn’t already know the correct answer, adding an outsider
              versus an insider actually doubled their chance of arriving at the correct solution, from
              29% to 60%. The work felt harder, but the outcomes were better.
                     In fact, working on diverse teams produces better outcomes precisely because
              it’s harder.

                     This idea goes against many people’s intuitions. There’s a common bias that
              psychologists call the fluency heuristic: We prefer information that is processed more
              easily, or fluently, judging it to be truer or more beautiful. The effect partially explains
              that we gain greater appreciation of songs or paintings when they become familiar
              because they’re more easily processed. The fluency heuristic leads many people to
              study incorrectly; they often simply reread the material. The information becomes

              more familiar without much effort, and so they feel that they’re learning. But in a
              2011 study students performed better on a test after studying the text once and then
              trying to recall as much as they could, a strenuous task, than they did by repeatedly
              going  over  the  text,  even  though  they  predicted  that  rereading  was  the  key  to
              learning. Similarly, confronting opinions you disagree with might not seem like the
              quickest path to getting things done, but working in groups can be like studying (or
              exercising): no pain, no gain.
                     Diversity Can Increase Conflict, but Not as Much as You Think

                     There’s another bias at play here, too: A 2015 paper in Organization Science,
              summarized in this HBR article, suggests that people overestimate the amount of
              conflict that actually exists on diverse teams. In one study MBA students were asked
              to imagine that they were comanaging several four-person teams of interns, and that
              one  team  had  asked  for  additional  resources.  They  saw  photos  of  the  members,
              depicting four white men, four black men, or two of each. They then read a transcript
              of a discussion among the group and rated the team on various factors. Teams of four

              white  men  and  four  black  men  were  seen  as  having  equal  levels  of  relationship
              conflict, but the diverse teams were seen as having more relationship conflict than
              the  homogeneous  teams,  even  though  everyone  had  read  the  same  transcript.
              Further, this perception of greater conflict made the participants less likely to provide
              the additional resources the mixed group had requested.
                     This type of unconscious bias can clearly have a significant impact not only on
              hiring  but  also  on  the  ways  in  which  leaders  create  teams  and  encourage
              collaboration.  Without realizing it, they may be reluctant to add diversity to a team

              or to assign colleagues with different backgrounds to work together, in response to
              an (overblown) fear of the tension and difficulty that could ensue.
                     Capitalizing on Diversity Means Highlighting — Not Hiding from — Differences


                                                             69]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[It’s critical to note that simply making a team more diverse is not necessarily

           enough  to  see  the  benefits.  Diverse  teams  must  find  ways  to  work  together
           productively, and often the best ways of working may seem counterintuitive.
                  For example, research suggests that when people with different perspectives
           are brought together, people may seek to gloss over those differences in the interest
           of group harmony — when, in fact, differences should actually be taken seriously and
           highlighted. In a 2012 study teams of three were tasked with generating a creative
           business plan for a theater. On some teams, members were assigned distinct roles
           (Artistic, Event, and Finance Manager), thus increasing diversity of viewpoints. These

           teams came up with better ideas than homogeneous teams — but only if they’d been
           explicitly told to try to take the perspectives of their teammates. They had to face up
           to their differences in order to benefit from them.
                  Another way to take advantage of differing viewpoints is to highlight the value
           of multiculturalism. One 2009 study looked at support for multiculturalism versus
           colorblindness in nearly 4,000 employees in 18 work units at a large U.S. health care

           firm. The more that workers agreed that “employees should recognize and celebrate
           racial and ethnic differences” and the more they disagreed that “employees should
           downplay their racial and ethnic differences,” the more that minorities in those units
           reported feeling engaged in their work. In another 2009 study, pairs of students, one
           white and one Aboriginal Canadian, were teamed up for a conversation. Prefacing the
           meeting with a message supporting multiculturalism (versus no message) made the
           meeting more positive, while a message endorsing colorblindness led whites to turn
           negative toward their minority partners.

                  Of  course,  diversity  is  not  always  a  panacea,  and  it  can  at  times  produce
           corrosive conflict. When that happens, it is often because team members are bringing
           different values, rather than different ideas, to the table. It’s difficult to overcome
           differences in values, no matter how well-intentioned colleagues may be. In addition,
           diversity’s  benefits  are  rarely  obtained  without  a  strong  sense  of  team  and
           organizational inclusion. Only when people feel welcome and respected will the team
           be able to benefit from their unique perspective and experience.

                  The  research  presented  here  suggests  that  diversity  initiatives  may  not  be
           successful until we do more to address the way diversity is perceived. When leaders
           see it first and foremost as a social obligation that makes things difficult and slows
           progress, they will likely make decisions that undermine the organization’s diversity
           goals. They may also, at least unconsciously, try to downplay the substance of existing
           diversity  on  their  teams.  If,  however,  leaders  can  recognize  that  the  debate  and
           unfamiliarity that come with diversity is an important catalyst for creativity and deep
           thinking, they will invite it and celebrate it. And very likely, the organization — and

           everyone in it — will reap the rewards.
           By David Rock, Heidi Grant, and Jacqui Grey for Harvard Business Review (HBR),
           September 22, 2016


                                                         70]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Link: https://hbr.org/2016/09/diverse-teams-feel-less-comfortable-and-thats-why-

              they-perform-better

                                                          NOTES
              Diversity – разнообразие: это любое измерение, которое можно использовать
              для  дифференциации  групп  и  людей  друг  от  друга.  Вкратце,  речь  идет  о
              расширении прав и возможностей людей путем уважения и оценки того, что
              отличает  их  с  точки  зрения  возраста,  пола,  этнической  принадлежности,
              религии, инвалидности, сексуальной ориентации, образования и национального

              происхождения.
              Homogenous team – однородная команда: состоит из людей, очень похожих друг
              на  друга,  имеющих  сходные  точки  зрения,  обучающийся  жизненный  опыт  и
              способности.
              Fraternity  or  sorority  –  братское  или  женское  общество:  это  братство  или
              сестричество, сформированное вокруг общих целей и стремлений. Эти мужчины

              и женщины берут на себя обязательства друг перед другом на всю жизнь. Члены,
              образующие  братство  или  женское  общество,  делятся  своими  усилиями,
              дружбой и знаниями.
              Bias – предвзятость: это несоразмерный вес в пользу или против идеи или вещи,
              обычно непредубежденный, предвзятый или несправедливый. Предубеждения
              могут  быть  врожденными  или  приобретенными.  У  людей  могут  развиться
              предубеждения за или против отдельного человека, группы или убеждения.
              Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin – Бюллетень личности и социальной

              психологии:  научный  журнал,  ежемесячно  издаваемый  издательством  SAGE
              Publications для Общества психологии личности и социальной психологии (SPSP).
              Fluency heuristic – эвристика беглости (психология): это ментальная эвристика, в
              которой,  если  один  объект  обрабатывается  более  быстро  или  плавно,  чем
              другой, разум делает вывод, что этот объект имеет более высокую ценность по
              отношению к рассматриваемому вопросу. Другими словами, чем искуснее или
              элегантнее  изложена  идея,  тем  больше  вероятность  того,  что  ее  будут

              рассматривать всерьез, независимо от того, логична она или нет.
              Organization Science – рецензируемый академический журнал, выходящий два
              раза в месяц Институтом исследований операций и управленческих наук (The
              Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences (INFORMS). Журнал
              охватывает исследования в области динамики организаций.
              HBR  (Harvard  Business  Review)  —  ежемесячный  научно-популярный  журнал,
              посвящённый различным вопросам управления бизнесом. Издаётся с 1922 года
              Гарвардской школой бизнеса.

              MBA       (Master      of     Business      Administration)       –     магистр      делового
              администрирования:  квалификационная  степень  магистра  в  менеджменте
              (управлении). Квалификация MBA подразумевает способность выполнять работу
              руководителя  среднего  и  высшего  звена.  Период  обучения  в  зависимости  от
                                                             71]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[начальной подготовки и конкретной программы занимает от двух до пяти лет.

           Технология  обучения  основана  на  методе  кейс-стади.  Первые  прототипы
           современных программ MBA появились в США в конце XIX века.
           Multiculturalism – мультикультурализм: политика, направленная на сохранение
           и развитие в отдельно взятой стране и в мире в целом культурных различий, и
           обосновывающая такую политику теория или идеология. Мультикультурализм
           противопоставляется  концепции  «плавильного  котла»,  где  предполагается
           слияние всех культур в одну.
           Colorblindness – дальтонизм: снижение способности видеть цвет или различия в

           цвете.

           VOCABULARY

                racial or gender diversity                      counterproductive
                revenue                                         solution

                customer                                        outcome
                profit                                          strenuous task
                executive                                       perception
                management team                                 unconscious bias
                team performance                                impact
                innovative product                              to gloss over (smth.)
                to deliberate                                   to downplay
                scrutiny                                        racial and ethnic differences

                bottom line                                     minority
                to recruit and retain                           to endorse
                workforce                                       to overcome
                marginal success                                organizational inclusion
                headway                                         social obligation
                political or religious affiliation              undermine
                collaboration                                   catalyst

                friction                                        reap the rewards
                insider                                         corrosive conflict
                outsider

           A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult a dictionary if necessary.
           1. Around 33 per cent of Indian businesses feel the need to become environmentally
           sustainable in order to recruit and retain the best people.
           2. The 2003 tour achieved only marginal success with many fans staying away,

           presumably because of high ticket prices.
           3. The incidence of absolute poverty has decreased and some headway has been
           made in advancing our human-development policy.
           4. This mechanism ensure that the outcome is fair and unpredictable.
                                                         72]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[5. Surely, to educate the educator, one must work for it as arduously as you worked

              in politics - only it is a much more strenuous task which demands deep psychological
              insight.
              6. The major's 2019 objectives include exploring the impact of unconscious bias, a
              refreshed framework to ensure talent is identified in a fair and consistent way and a
              project that examines the job applicant's experience in terms of diversity.
              7. However, no socio-political processes were able to gloss over the ethnic
              individuality and national self-expression of the Kazakh people.
              8. No self-respecting country could endorse that approach.

              9. Services that fulfill social obligation to enhance competitiveness in
              entrepreneurship.
              10. Poverty and under-development undermine security and democracy.
              11. Today you will reap the rewards for your hard work over the last month, in every
              aspect of your life.
              12. They evaluate overall team performance and work closely with managers in

              other departments.
              13. In general, socially responsible investors encourage corporate practices that they
              believe promote environmental stewardship, consumer protection, human rights,
              and racial or gender diversity.
              14. Company's management team, as well as all our employees, is fully aware of our
              environmental liability.
              15. With 40 years of experience and innovative product development, the company
              is ready to meet the demands of today's ever-changing market.


              B. Find in the text the English for:
              социальное  обязательство;  бессознательное  предубеждение  (предвзятость);
              политическая  или  религиозная  принадлежность;  сотрудничество;  трение;
              инсайдер,  свой  человек;  аутсайдер,  посторонний  человек;  воздействие;
              приукрашивать  (что-л.);  преуменьшать;  расовые  и  этнические  различия;
              преодолеть;  организационное  включение  (инклюзия);  подрывать  (ослабить);

              катализатор;  пожинать  плоды;  разрушительный  конфликт;  расовое  или
              гендерное  разнообразие;  доход,  выручка;  клиент;  выгода;  управляющий,
              исполнительный;  контрпродуктивный;  решение;  результат,  исход;  трудная
              (напряженная)  задача;  восприятие;  руководящая  группа;  производительность
              команды; инновационный продукт; взвешивать; внимательное рассмотрение;
              нижняя линия, суть дела; нанимать и удерживать; рабочая сила; ограниченный
              успех; прогресс; меньшинство; одобрять.


              C. Translate into Russian.
              7 Small Ways to Be a More Inclusive Colleague
              Helping  to  increase  inclusivity  at  your  workplace  doesn’t  necessarily  require  an
              extensive DEI campaign. It also doesn’t require you to be in a position of power. Each
                                                             73]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[and every one of us can decide to be an inclusive colleague and take small actions

           every day to improve our workplace culture.
           By making small changes in your own behavior, you can generate disproportionate
           positive effects on your colleagues’ workplace experience. Similar to small deposits
           earning interest in a long-term savings account, your actions will have large impacts
           over the longer term. The key is to identify behavior changes that you can perform
           repeatedly and turn into habits so they become automatic.
           Inclusion  within  an  organization  means  accepting  and  valuing  each  and  every
           colleague’s talents and qualities — without imposing conformity. When this happens,

           not only are employees happier at work, but the organization benefits from their
           unique insights and heightened productivity.
           Here are seven small actions you can take to be a more inclusive colleague and help
           foster a comfortable and safe work environment for everyone.
           1. Highlight others’ contributions.
           Visibility at work allows individuals to showcase their abilities, be known to decision

           makers,  and  build  relationships.  Research  validates  that  the  contributions  of
           disadvantaged groups, like Asian minorities in Western countries, are systematically
           overlooked.
           Identify  a  highly  competent  colleague  who  may  lack  visibility  and  highlight  their
           achievements by publicly acknowledging their contributions and encouraging them
           to speak and present in meetings.
           2. Use your pronouns.
           Including your pronouns when you introduce yourself at meetings is a small action

           that signals that you’re an ally to colleagues who may struggle to voice that they’re
           often  referred  to  with  pronouns  they  don’t  identify  with.  It  also  normalizes  the
           practice for your other colleagues.
           3. Use gender-inclusive language.
           Research has shown that using gender-inclusive language at work is associated with
           better well-being for employees who identify as LGBTQ, so ensure that the language
           you use is gender-neutral. For example, using “people” instead of “guys” can make

           everyone feel included.
           4. Assess your vocabulary.
           Many  common  slang  words  have  other  connotations  or  origins  and  should  be
           avoided. For example, the word “lame” is often used to describe something as boring
           or  monotonous,  but  it  was  originally  used  to  refer  to  individuals  with  impaired
           mobility. Similarly, the common use of the terms “tribalism” or “tribal mindset” to
           describe out-group behavior is based on a racial stereotype of Indigenous people
           during colonial times. Actively assess your vocabulary for slang terms that alienate

           others.
           5. Celebrate with your colleagues.
           A diverse workplace is made up of people from various backgrounds who celebrate
           different festivities, be they religious (like Eid for Muslims) or historic (like Pride or
                                                         74]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Black History month). Enabling others to celebrate these occasions and participate in

              organized  events  is  a  wonderful  way  to  acknowledge  individualism.  Even  better,
              celebrating these occasions along with your colleagues can go a long way toward
              making  them  feel  accepted  and  boosting  their  morale,  in  addition  to  building
              psychological safety.
              6. Get creative about team bonding.
              While putting together team-bonding activities, factor in the availability and interest
              of all your team members. If every social event is drinks at a pub in the evening, that
              might hinder participation from some caregivers, parents, remote employees, and

              people who don’t drink alcohol. Instead, consider activities like virtual coffee chats,
              volunteer work, and online games like Pictionary or trivia. Ensuring that everyone gets
              to participate in as many team activities as possible will help the team truly bond and
              have fun together.
              7. Be curious.
              Schedule coffees and lunches with colleagues who have different backgrounds than

              you. Without being intrusive, take an interest in their lived experience inside and
              outside the office. Use what you learn to devise additional small actions to undertake
              as an inclusive colleague.
                                                             . . .
              Workplace  inclusion  is  not  a  static,  one-off  act  of  service.  It’s  an  ever-evolving
              experience that requires the contribution of every employee — regardless of their
              level of seniority in the organization — to make each other feel included. To foster
              inclusion  around  you,  form  and  regularly  practice  inclusive  behaviors  until  they

              become habitual and automatic. Starting with these small actions can enable you to
              transform the level of inclusivity in your team.
              By Nikita and Grace Lordan for Harvard Business Review (HBR), February 2, 2023
              Link: https://hbr.org/2023/02/7-small-ways-to-be-a-more-inclusive-colleague





























                                                             75]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[UNIT IX. TRADE & PROFESSIONAL

                                                      TEXT 9A

                  New Brexit trading rules could take more than two years to bed in fully

                   The new Brexit trading arrangements in Rishi Sunak’s revised Northern Ireland

           protocol  could  take  more  than  two  years  to  be  fully  implemented,  government
           sources have confirmed.
                   Businesses in Northern Ireland say they expect a mass educational campaign
           to be launched across the country by HMRC and other government departments to
           help them put the deal announced in Windsor last Monday into operation if it is
           approved by parliament.
                   But with legislation required to bring the Windsor framework into force, the

           first of the new measures could take months to become operational.
                   A  government  source  said  if  the  new  deal  was  ratified  it  would  be
           “intentionally giving industry time to prepare. Essentially, it is a phased introduction
           over this year and in 2024.”
                   However, the introduction of updated labelling for products travelling across
           the Irish Sea via the new customs “green lane” will be staggered, with the last stage
           being implemented as late as July 2025.
                   Businesses are still trying to work out what the deal means for them. “It is

           important to emphasise this is a framework but there’s a lot of operational detail to
           work  through,”  said  Stuart  Anderson,  the  head  of  public  affairs  at  the  Northern
           Ireland chamber of commerce.
                   “There  is  also  a  quite  significant  political,  practical  and  legal  work  to  get
           through as part of the process. For example, the timeline for labelling is until July 2025
           underlining that this is very much a process over time.”

                   Labelling products as “not for the EU” will be one of the most visible changes
           to result from Brexit in Northern Ireland and the rest of the UK.
                   Under the new arrangements producers of fresh meats, such as sausages, and
           dairy products will have to start labelling goods for sale in Northern Ireland from this
           October. The government has promised swift reimbursement to cover the cost.
                   From October next year, labelling requirements will be extended to include all
           other dairy products, such as UHT milk and butter, across the UK. The final phase of
           labelling will enter into force in July 2025 and apply to fish, fruit and vegetables and
           composite products such as ready meals.

                   Both the Northern Ireland chamber of commerce and Manufacturing NI say
           they are confident that businesses will be able to work with government to bring the
           new rules into operation.
                   “As businesses we had to shout from the sidelines in the past, sometimes we
           had to kick down the doors to get heard but now we know we are going to be invited
                                                         76]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[into the room,” said Stephen Kelly, the chief executive of Manufacturing NI, one of a

              group of business representatives who met Sunak last week.
                       The process to bring the deal into operation will start later this month after a
              meeting of the UK-EU joint committee, a body established to enforce the original
              withdrawal agreement.
                       Legislation  may  be  needed  for  some  elements  of  the  deal  such  as  the
              application of UK VAT rules and alcohol duties in Northern Ireland, but sources say
              that could happen swiftly.
                       Kelly said some of the “low-hanging fruit” such as the tariff reimbursement

              schemes could be up and running by early summer.
                       This is a repayment scheme for any businesses that are not certain of the end
              destination of their product but who bring materials in through the red lane and pay
              an EU tariff on a component. If that product ends up being sold and remaining in
              Northern Ireland they can claim back the tariff.
                       “We expect HMRC will have to implement changes to some systems and a

              campaign to educate traders, but there are relatively simple things they could get
              started with in the early summer.”
                       Farmers will also be looking for a swift enactment of the Windsor clauses that
              reverse bans on the importation from Great Britain of seed potatoes and 11 native
              British trees, along with a relaxation of rules regarding secondhand farm machinery.
                       Months after the protocol came in in 2021, the Woodland Trust was forced to
              cancel the purchase of 22,000 trees for communities and schools in Northern Ireland
              because of the restrictions.

              By Lisa O'Carroll for The Guardian, March 6, 2023
                       Link:  https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2023/mar/05/northern-ireland-
              new-brexit-trade-rules-could-take-more-than-two-years-to-bed-in-fully

                                                          NOTES
              Brexit  –  сокращено  от  «Britain  Exit»:  Выход  Великобритании  из  Европейского
              союза  -  прекращение  членства  Великобритании  в  Европейском  союзе  и

              связанная с ним процедура.
              HMRC  -  Her  Majesty's  Revenue  and  Customs:  Управление  по  налоговым  и
              таможенным сборам Её Величества – это налоговый, платежный и таможенный
              орган Великобритании.
              Windsor  framework:  Виндзорские  рамки  -  это  предлагаемое  юридическое
              соглашение  между  Европейским  союзом  и  Великобританией  после  Brexit,  о
              котором  было  объявлено  27  февраля  2023  года.  Оно  предназначено  для
              решения проблемы перемещения товаров между Единым европейским рынком

              и Великобританией в действующий Протокол Северной Ирландии.
              Woodland  Trust  -  крупнейшая  в  Великобритании  благотворительная
              организация по сохранению лесов и деревьев.


                                                             77]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[UK  -  The  United  Kingdom  of  Great  Britain  and  Northern  Ireland:  Соединенное

           Королевство  Великобритании  и  Северной  Ирландии,  широко  известное  как
           Соединенное Королевство (United Kingdom) или Великобритания (Great Britain),
           представляет  собой  страну  в  Европе,  расположенную  у  северо-западного
           побережья континентального материка. Включает в себя Англию, Шотландию,
           Уэльс и Северную Ирландию.
           EU  –  the  European  Union:  Европейский  союз  (ЕС)  -  наднациональный
           политический  и  экономический  союз  27  государств-членов,  расположенных
           преимущественно в Европе.

           VAT  -  value-added  tax:  налог  на  добавленную  стоимость  (НДС),  известный  в
           некоторых странах как налог на товары и услуги, представляет собой тип налога,
           который начисляется поэтапно.
           UHT - ultra-high temperature processing: ультравысокотемпературная обработка -
           это  технология  обработки  пищевых  продуктов,  при  которой  жидкая  пища
           стерилизуется  путем  ее  нагревания  до  температуры  выше  135  °C  (275  °F)  -

           температуры, необходимой для уничтожения бактериальных эндоспор - от 2 до
           5 секунд.

           VOCABULARY

                trading arrangement                             labelling
                protocol                                        swift reimbursement
                implement                                       joint committee

                mass educational campaign                       withdrawal agreement
                government department                           tariff reimbursement schemes
                deal                                            repayment scheme
                to bring into force                             swift enactment
                to ratify                                       purchase
                framework                                       relaxation of rules
                head of public affairs                          restrictions

                chamber of commerce                             secondhand farm machinery


           A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult a dictionary if necessary.
              1.  Sweden therefore continues to urge all states to conclude and bring into force
                  Additional Protocols.
              2.  The legislative framework is sufficient to address any weapons offences.
              3.  The need for swift reimbursement of troop-contributing countries was

                  stressed by many delegations.
              4.  A joint committee is responsible for monitoring the proper working of the
                  agreement.
              5.  Make sure every purchase you make is smart.
                                                         78]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[6.  Considering relaxation of rules and restrictions at border crossings for

                     legitimate travellers on the basis of reciprocal arrangements.
                  7.  Businesses have become increasingly alarmed by the slow progress of
                     negotiations and the prospect that the country could leave the trading bloc
                     without a new trading arrangement in place in 2019.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              схема  возмещения  тарифов;  сделка;  ввести  в  действие;  маркировка;
              оперативное возмещение расходов; совместный комитет; соглашение о выходе;

              схема  погашения;  ослабление  правил;  ограничения;  ратифицировать;
              концептуальные  рамки;  руководитель  службы  по  связям  с  общественностью;
              торговая  палата;  подержанная  сельскохозяйственная  техника;  организация
              торговых  процессов;  протокол;  осуществлять;  массовая  образовательно-
              информационная            кампания;        правительственное          учреждение          (либо
              «министерство»); быстрое введение в действие; покупка.


              C. Translate into Russian.
              How is the government's Brexit deal with the European Union going down?
              Plenty  of  people  in  government  involved  in  delivering  the  so-called  Windsor
              Framework are wiped out.
              A deficit of fresh air, sleep and time with their families continues, as they observe the
              reaction to what they have spent months working on.
              At least one of Rishi Sunak's biggest political supporters had initially tried to put him

              off taking this on. "There are no runs in it," one said to me, suggesting the prime
              minister "leave it to Keir Starmer to sort out."
              Impressed that he had managed to strike a deal, this ally compared it to the Downing
              Street Declaration of 1993, widely seen as a vital staging post in the Northern Ireland
              Peace Process.
              The  point  my  source  was  making  was  that  Sir  John  Major's  achievement  then,
              alongside his Irish opposite number Albert Reynolds, was not rewarded at the ballot

              box a few years later.
              But  this  former  minister  reflected  that  it  can  help  demonstrate  a  seriousness  of
              purpose and achievement in Rishi Sunak's government, that critics will say the last
              two prime ministers lacked.
              So how is it going down?
              The prime minister has become something of a travelling salesman for his deal: taking
              in Windsor, parliament, Northern Ireland and parliament again in just over 24 hours.
              Rishi Sunak is confident the substance of what he has negotiated is a good deal,

              grounded in a strong personal relationship with the European Commission President
              Ursula von der Leyen, and one based on mutual trust.
              But this is where it encounters domestic politics.


                                                             79]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[Firstly, it's worth spelling out what hasn't happened. There hasn't been an almighty

           row within his own party, a re-ignition of the volcanic ructions you might have noticed
           in the last year or two. That, in itself, is an achievement.
           More than that, there have been some Conservative MPs - who expected to be critics
           - finding themselves sounding positive. It is as if, in complimenting the government
           for its strategy around Brexit, they are suddenly exercising muscles in their jaw they
           didn't realise they had.
           One said they thought they would have to "eat humble pie" and admit their initial
           instinct "was wrong" and that "Rishi has squared the circle."

           By Chris Mason, Political editor, for BBC News, March 1, 2023
           Link: https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-politics-64806466

                                                      TEXT 9B

           UK-Asia trade deal to boost UK economy by 0.08%

           The UK has signed a deal to join a trade pact with 11 Asia and Pacific nations, three
           years after it officially left the European Union.

                   Joining the group will boost UK exports by cutting tariffs on goods such as
           cheese, cars, chocolate, machinery, gin and whisky, the government said.
                   However, the government's own estimates show being in the bloc will only
           add 0.08% to the size of the UK's economy.
                   The trade area covers a market of around 500 million people.

                   The Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership
           - or CPTPP - was established in 2018, and includes Australia, Brunei, Canada, Chile,
           Japan, Malaysia, Mexico, New Zealand, Peru, Singapore and Vietnam.
                   Membership of the CPTPP loosens restrictions on trade between members
           and reduce tariffs - a form of border tax - on goods.
                   UK to join Asia's trade club - what is the CPTPP?
                   Together, the 11 members account for about 13% of the world's income and

           after 21 months of negotiations, the UK has become the first European country to
           join.
                   The government said the agreement was the UK's "biggest trade deal since
           Brexit".
                   However, the gains for the UK from joining are expected to be modest. The
           UK already has free trade deals with all of the members except Brunei and Malaysia,
           some of which were rolled over from its previous membership of the EU.
                   And even with some gains in trading the government only estimates it will add

           0.08% to the size of the economy in 10 years. The Office for Budget Responsibility
           (OBR), which provides forecasts for the government, has previously said Brexit would
           reduce the UK's potential economic growth by about 4% in the long term.

                                                         80]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA['Prime position'

                       But Prime Minister Rishi Sunak said the deal demonstrated the "real economic
              benefits of our post-Brexit freedoms".
                       "As part of CPTPP, the UK is now in a prime position in the global economy to
              seize opportunities for new jobs, growth and innovation," he said.
                       "British businesses will now enjoy unparalleled access to markets from Europe
              to the south Pacific."
                       Business and Trade Secretary Kemi Badenoch said the agreement was like
              "buying a start-up".

                       "This is not to replace EU trade, this is in addition. We are still in a free trade
              agreement with the EU," she told Radio 4's Today programme.
                       "You wouldn't buy a small company like that and expect it to be delivering on
              the day - we are thinking about the potential," she said, adding that in seven years
              "40% of the world's middle class is going to come from that region".
                       Ms Badenoch denied there would be any hit to UK agriculture, saying the deal

              would "create new markets" for farmers.
                       Labour's shadow international trade secretary Nick Thomas-Symonds said the
              UK  joining  the  CPTPP  was  "encouraging",  but  added  that  questions  remain  on
              "consumer safety, food safety, data protection and environmental protections".
                       The government said other "benefits" of being in the bloc included, a boost to
              the services sector, by UK firms not being required to establish a local office or be
              resident to supply a service, meaning they will be on a par with local firms.
                       The government said it and CPTPP members would make the final legal and

              administrative steps required for the UK to formally sign in 2023.
              By Tom Espiner (Business reporter) for BBC News, March 31, 2023
              Link: https://www.bbc.com/news/business-65124741

                                                          NOTES
              Brexit  -  сокращено  от  «Britain  Exit»:  Выход  Великобритании  из  Европейского
              союза  -  прекращение  членства  Великобритании  в  Европейском  союзе  и

              связанная с ним процедура.
              The  European  Union  (EU)  -  Европейский  союз  (ЕС):  наднациональный
              политический  и  экономический  союз  27  государств-членов,  расположенных
              преимущественно в Европе
              Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership (CPTPP) -
              Всеобъемлющее  и  прогрессивное  соглашение  о  Транстихоокеанском
              партнерстве  (ВПСТТП):  представляет  собой  торговое  соглашение  между
              Австралией, Брунеем, Канадой, Чили, Японией, Малайзией, Мексикой, Новой

              Зеландией,       Перу,     Сингапуром        и     Вьетнам,      возникшее        на    основе
              Транстихоокеанского партнерства (ТТП), которое так и не было ратифицировано
              из-за выхода США.


                                                             81]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR) - Управление бюджетной ответственности

           (УБО):  проводит  независимый  и  авторитетный  анализ  государственных
           финансов Великобритании.
           Prime Minister of the UK - Премьер-министр Великобритании: является главой
           правительства  Великобритании.  Премьер-министр  консультирует  монарха  по
           поводу  осуществления  большей  части  королевской  прерогативы,  возглавляет
           кабинет и выбирает его министров. Поскольку современные премьер-министры
           занимают  свои  посты  благодаря  своей  способности  пользоваться  доверием
           Палаты общин, они заседают в качестве членов парламента.

           Business  and  Trade  Secretary  –  Министр  по  делам  бизнеса  и  торговли
           Великобритании.

           VOCABULARY

            trade deal                                              forecast

            to boost                                                global economy
            trade pact                                              to seize opportunities
            export                                                  economic benefit
            cutting tariffs                                         growth and innovation
            goods                                                   unparalleled access
            to estimate                                             free trade agreement
            bloc                                                    agriculture
            economy                                                 create new markets

            market                                                  labour
            comprehensive and progressive agreement                 consumer safety
            Trans-Pacific                                           data protection
            partnership                                             environmental protection
            membership                                              services sector
            reduce tariffs                                          resident
            border tax                                              to be on a par with

            income                                                  local firm
            negotiations                                            legal and administrative steps
            gains in trading                                        budget
            potential economic growth in the long term



           A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult a dictionary if necessary.
              1.  But a year later, the remaining 11 countries announced that they would be
                  moving  forward,  based  on  the  so-called  Comprehensive  and  Progressive
                  Agreement for the TPP.
              2.  And the collapse or merger of many of its competitors has enabled it to make


                                                         82]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[big gains in trading for clients.

                  3.  The key is understanding consumer behaviour then adjusting your priorities in
                     order to seize opportunities.
                  4.  The potential economic growth of 1.5 percent in annual terms is limited for the
                     most part by labour shortages.
                  5.  It's not  a secret that obvious  economic benefit  significantly accelerates  the
                     implementation of any legislation.
                  6.  Participants agreed to implement a regional free trade agreement and develop
                     a transportation corridor.

                  7.  The strategic objective of the Head of State is the intention to be on a par with
                     the advanced and civilized countries.
                  8.  Take the legal and administrative steps necessary to guarantee that admission
                     and enrollment criteria for girls are applied in the same way as for boys.

              B. Find in the text the English for:

              глобальная экономика; партнерство; членство; доход; переговоры; прибыль в
              торговли;  бюджет;  прогноз;  использовать  возможности;  потенциальный
              экономический рост; в долгосрочной перспективе; экономическая выгода; рост
              и  инновации;  беспрецедентный  доступ;  соглашение  о  свободной  торговле;
              создавать  новые  рынки;  труд;  безопасность  потребителей;  защита  данных;
              защита окружающей среды; сектор услуг; повысить; торговый договор; товары;
              оценить;  союз;  экономика;  рынок;  всеобъемлющее  и  прогрессивное
              соглашение; Транстихоокеанский; быть наравне с; местная фирма; правовые и

              административные  меры;  торговая  сделка;  пограничный  налог;  экспорт;
              снижение тарифов; житель; сельское хозяйство; снижать тарифы.

              C.  Translate into Russian.
              Boris Johnson says prospect of trans-Pacific trade deal is 'exciting opportunity' as
              Dominic Raab begins negotiations
              Joining a trans-Pacific trade deal is an "exciting opportunity" for the UK to build on its

              "entrepreneurial spirit and free-trading history", Boris Johnson has said.
              Foreign Secretary Dominic Raab has entered three days of negotiations over the UK
              becoming part of the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for trans-Pacific
              Partnership (CPTPP).
              The  PM  said  the  possible  free  trade  agreement,  which  exists  between  Australia,
              Brunei, Canada, Chile, Japan, Malaysia, Mexico, New Zealand, Peru, Singapore and
              Vietnam, would create "unparalleled opportunities for the UK».
              Earlier this month, the CPTPP announced that the accession process would begin

              following the UK's application to join the agreement in February.
              Mr  Raab  landed  in  Hanoi,  Vietnam  on  Monday  ahead  of  the  accession  process
              formally getting under way on Tuesday.


                                                             83]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[Ahead of the talks launching, the PM said: "Membership of the CPTTP free-trade

           partnership  would  open  up  unparalleled  opportunities  for  British  businesses  and
           consumers in the fast-growing Indo-Pacific.
           "It's an exciting opportunity to build on this country's entrepreneurial spirit and free-
           trading history to bring economic benefits across the whole of the UK».
           The UK already has trade agreements with seven CTPP members, including - most
           recently - Australia.
           But the government said CPTPP membership would allow the UK access to some of
           the world's biggest economies, with members having a combined GDP of £9 trn.

           They added that joining the alliance would lower tariffs on British cars and whisky -
           with tariff-free trade for 99.9% of exports - and help British farmers sell beef and lamb
           into fellow CPTPP countries.
           International Trade Secretary Liz Truss described CPTPP membership as "a glittering
           post-Brexit prize" for the UK.
           "This part of the world is where Britain's greatest opportunities lie. We left the EU

           with  the  promise  of  deepening  links  with  old  allies  and  fast-growing  consumer
           markets beyond Europe, and joining the high-standards trans-Pacific Partnership is an
           important part of that vision," she said.
           "Membership would help our farmers, makers and innovators sell to some of the
           biggest economies of the present and future, but without ceding control over our
           laws, borders or money. It is a glittering post-Brexit prize that I want us to seize».
           And  speaking  ahead  of  the  visit,  Mr  Raab  added:  "The  UK  is  committed  to
           strengthening our friendship across the Indo-Pacific.

           "We are demonstrating this through our commitment to join CPTPP, partner with
           ASEAN (the Association of Southeast Asian Nations) and invest more energy, time and
           effort in our bilateral relations in the region."
           While in Vietnam, the foreign secretary will also meet Vietnamese leaders, including
           President Nguyen Xuan Phuc, Deputy Prime Minister Pham Binh Minh and foreign
           minister Bui Thanh Son.
           He will then travel to Cambodia to meet foreign minister Prak Sokhonn - the first visit

           to the country by a UK foreign secretary since the British Embassy reopened there 30
           years ago.
           From there, Mr Raab will travel to Singapore and meet Prime Minister Lee Hsien
           Loong and foreign minister Vivian Balakrishnan.
           By Sophie Morris, Political Reporter, for Sky News, June 22, 2021
           Link: https://news.sky.com/story/boris-johnson-says-prospect-of-trans-pacific-trade-
           deal-is-exciting-opportunity-as-dominic-raab-begins-negotiations-12338098









                                                         84]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[UNIT X. KZ/UK MEDIA


                                                         TEXT 10A

              US President Joe Biden to visit UK after invite from King Charles
              US President Joe Biden has accepted an invitation from King Charles to go to the UK
              on a state visit.

                       The King invited the US president during a recent telephone call.
                       The  White  House  said  Mr  Biden  had  a  "friendly  conversation"  with  the
              monarch where they also discussed his mother, the late Queen Elizabeth II.
                       During the call, President Biden confirmed he would not be attending the
              coronation, but First Lady Jill Biden would represent the US at the event.
                       King Charles' coronation will take place at Westminster Abbey in London on 6
              May.

                       In addition to the Royal Family, those attending the coronation will include the
              prime minister, representatives from the Houses of Parliament, heads of state, and
              other royals from around the world.
                       What we know about King Charles's coronation
                       White  House  spokesperson  Karine  Jean-Pierre  said  the  president  was
              "appreciative" of the offer from King Charles and "looks forward" to the visit.
                       "During that call the King offered for him [Biden] to come and do a state visit
              which the president accepted", Ms Jean-Pierre told reporters.

                       "So they will see each other again very soon."
                       She said the King and President Biden "have a good relationship" and share
              common values on issues such as climate change.
                       During the call on Tuesday, which lasted between 25 and 30 minutes, Ms Jean-
              Pierre  said  the  president  discussed  how  he  enjoyed  meeting  the  late  Queen  at
              Windsor in 2021.

                       She said there was currently no timeframe for the visit, but it would be "in the
              near future".
                       Mr Biden visited the UK with his wife Jill last year for the Queen's funeral.
                       The White House has also confirmed President Biden will begin a four-day trip
              to Northern Ireland and the Irish Republic in Belfast on 11 April.
                       This will mark the 25th anniversary of the Good Friday Agreement.
              BBC News, April 6, 2023
              Link: https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-65196188


                                                          NOTES
              King Charles III - Король Карл III (полное имя Чарльз Фили́пп Артур Джордж):
              царствующий  король  Великобритании  и  Северной  Ирландии  и  королевств
              Содружества  из  Виндзорской  династии,  верховный  главнокомандующий


                                                             85]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[вооружёнными силами Великобритании, верховный правитель Церкви Англии,

           глава Содружества наций с 8 сентября 2022 года.
           Joe  Biden  -  Джо  Байден  (полное  имя  Джо́зеф  Робине́тт  Ба́йден-мла́дший):
           американский государственный и политический деятель, член Демократической
           партии. Действующий 46-й президент США с 20 января 2021 года. Ранее — 47-й
           вице-президент США с 20 января 2009 года по 20 января 2017 года.
           The  White  House  -  Бе́лый  дом:  официальная  резиденция  президента  США,
           расположенная в Вашингтоне по почтовому адресу: Пенсильвания-авеню, 1600.
           First  Lady  the  United  States  -  первая  леди  США:  титул  хозяйки  Белого  дома.

           Традиционно первой леди является супруга президента США.
           Westminster  Abbey  -  Вестминстерское  аббатство:  готическая  церковь  в
           Вестминстере  (Лондон).  Строилась  с  перерывами  с  1245  по  1745  годы,  хотя
           первые  упоминания  о  церкви  на  этом  месте  относятся  к  VII—X  векам.
           Традиционное  место  коронации  и  захоронения  монархов  Великобритании.
           Вместе с расположенными рядом Вестминстерским дворцом и церковью Святой

           Маргариты аббатство в 1987 году было причислено ко Всемирному наследию.
           Queen Elizabeth II - Елизаве́та II (полное имя — Елизаве́та Алекса́ндра Мари́я) —
           королева Великобритании и Северной Ирландии и королевств Содружества из
           Виндзорской династии, верховный главнокомандующий вооружёнными силами
           Великобритании,  верховный  правитель  Церкви  Англии,  глава  Содружества
           наций с 6 февраля 1952 и до своей смерти 8 сентября 2022 года. Мать Короля
           Карла III.
           The British Royal Family - Британская королевская семья: состоит из короля Карла

           III  и  его  близких  родственников.  Они  поддерживают  монарха  в  проведении
           общественных  мероприятий  и  часто  занимаются  благотворительной
           деятельностью и интересами. Королевская семья считается иконой британской
           и мировой культуры.
           Houses of Parliament of the UK - Парламент Великобритании: двухпалатный, но
           состоит из трех частей - из монарха (короля в парламенте), Палаты лордов и
           Палаты общин (первичная палата).

           Good  Friday  Agreement  (GFA)  -  Соглашение  Страстной  пятницы,  оно  же
           Белфастское  соглашение:  соглашение  о  политическом  урегулировании
           конфликта  в  Северной  Ирландии,  предусматривавшее  создание  автономных
           органов  власти,  также  был  предложен  ряд  других  мер,  касающихся
           политических и конституционных аспектов североирландского конфликта.

           VOCABULARY


            monarch                                         appreciative
            coronation                                      offer
            invitation                                      share common values
            state visit                                     climate change issues
                                                         86]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[represent, representative                       the late Queen

               friendly conversation                           timeframe
               heads of state                                  The Queen’s funeral
               royals                                          in the near future
               spokesperson                                    anniversary

              A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult a dictionary if necessary.
              1. He stressed that the aim of his state visit to Brunei is to restore political dialogue
                and deepen bilateral trade, and economic cooperation.

              2. They share common values and a common commitment to international norms that
                recognize both the rights and responsibilities of all sovereign nations.
              3. The development of the energy sector today cannot be imagined without close
                attention to climate change issues.
              4. Last  night  the  spokesperson  for  the  Ministry  of  Defense  Artrun  Hovhannisyan
                informed that an Armenian citizen is currently in Azerbaijan.

              5. They also noted the impressive work accomplished during 2002 given the short
                timeframe.
              6. Membership is by invitation or recommendation only.
              7. We expect to announce several major initiatives in the near future.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              главы государств; проблемы изменения климата; официальный представитель,
              пресс-секретарь;  признательный;  предложение;  разделяют  общие  ценности;

              проблемы  изменения  климата;  покойная  королева;  временные  рамки;
              похороны королевы; в ближайшем будущем; годовщина; монарх; коронация;
              приглашение; государственный визит; представлять, представитель; дружеская
              беседа;  покойная  королева;  временные  рамки;  главы  государств;  члены
              королевской семьи; предложение; дружеская беседа.

              C. Translate into Russian.

              Joe Biden accepts King Charles’s invitation for state visit
              News  of  invitation  follows  announcement  that  US  president  will  visit  Ireland  and
              Northern Ireland next week
              Joe Biden has accepted an invitation from King Charles III for a state visit, a White
              House spokesperson has said.
              The invitation was made during a “friendly” 25 to 30 minute phone call in which Biden
              congratulated the king on his upcoming coronation, which the US president will not
              attend.

              This is in keeping with the tradition that US presidents do not attend British monarchs’
              coronations and follows the decision by President Eisenhower to skip Elizabeth II’s
              coronation in 1953.
              Instead, the first lady, Jill Biden, will represent the US on her husband’s behalf.
                                                             87]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[News of the invitation follows an announcement that the US president will be visiting

           Ireland and Northern Ireland next week, starting in Belfast before travelling to Dublin,
           with visits to County Louth and County Mayo, where Biden’s ancestors are from. He
           is also due to address the Irish parliament, the Oireachtas.
           The White House press secretary, Karine Jean-Pierre, said Biden had told King Charles
           how much he enjoyed visiting the Queen back in 2021 when he and the first lady came
           to Windsor, adding that he hoped to visit again soon.
           The  king  then  offered  for  Biden  to  come  for  a  state  visit,  which  the  president
           accepted, Jean-Pierre said.

           “So they will see each other again very soon, they have a very good relationship, there
           are many things that they both care about, key shared values, key shared issues, that
           they want to continue to discuss like climate change.
           She added: “I do not have a timeline, I can’t say when it will be but the president was
           appreciative of the offer by the king and looks forward to it.”
           A  Buckingham  Palace  spokesperson  said  they  would  not  comment  on  the

           arrangement.
           By Donna Ferguson for The Guardian, April 6, 2023
           Link: https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2023/apr/06/joe-biden-accepts-king-
           charless-invitation-for-state-visit

                                                     TEXT 10B

                      President Tokayev hosts Ramadan Iftar dinner in Akorda Palace


                   ASTANA.  KAZINFORM  On  Friday,  April  7,  Head  of  State  Kassym-Jomart
           Tokayev hosted Iftar dinner in the Akorda Palace to mark the holy month of Ramadan,
           Kazinform learned from the presidential press service.
                   Addressing  the  guests,  the  President  emphasized  special  importance  of
           Ramadan  for  all  Muslims,  the  month  which  people  devote  to  spiritual  self-
           improvement and good deeds, Kazinform reports citing the Akorda press service.

                   In his speech the Head of State touched upon a number of key events which
           occurred in the country’s socio-political life in the past year, namely the nationwide
           referendum  following  which  amendments  to  the  Constitution  were  adopted,
           presidential elections as well as the election of deputies to the lower chamber of the
           Parliament and the local maslikhats.
                   «We are strongly committed to continuing the policy of reforms» the Head of
           State said.
                   He noted that Kazakhstan will continue is active international cooperation,

           while the country’s foreign policy will remain independent. He stressed that peace
           and unity only may ensure the country's prosperity and achievement of the goals set.
           «Namely these enduring values underlie the state’s progress and people’s confidence


                                                         88]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[in  tomorrow.  Maintaining  peace  and  unity  in  Kazakhstan  is  one  of  our  major

              objectives» he pointed out.
                       «Promotion  of  traditional  Islam  in  accordance  with  spiritual  and  cultural
              requests of our society is of great importance today» the President stressed.
                       The  Head  of  State  called  also  to  preserve  and  develop  national  culture.
              «National culture is a mirror of the people’s life, while spiritual development of the
              country is directly linked to the development of national identity» Kassym-Jomart
              Tokayev highlighted.
                       Expressing concern about the current global situation, the President noted

              that today society lacks such universal human qualities as kindness, mercy and care
              of others. He called to exert every effort to overcome these disturbing trends that
              threaten entire humanity. For this, everyone should sacredly keep high principles in
              his heart and follow them in his daily thoughts and actions.
                       Kassym-Jomart Tokayev wished peace and well-being to his compatriots.
                       Prominent  statesmen  and  well-known  public  figures,  scientists,  doctors,

              teachers, representatives of ethno-cultural associations, heads of foreign missions,
              workers of culture and rescue services were invited to the Iftar dinner.
              By Arailym Temirgaliyeva for KAZINFORM, April 7, 2023
              Link: https://www.inform.kz/en/president-tokayev-hosts-ramadan-iftar-dinner-in-
              akorda-palace_a4054790

                                                          NOTES
              Kassym-Jomart  Tokayev  -  Касы́м-Жома́рт  Кеме́левич  Тока́ев:  казахстанский

              государственный и политический деятель. Действующий президент Республики
              Казахстан и верховный главнокомандующий вооружёнными силами Республики
              Казахстан с 20 марта 2019 года. Председатель Совета безопасности Республики
              Казахстан с 5 января 2022 года.
              Iftar – ифтар: вечерний приём пищи у мусульман во время исламского месяца
              Рамадан. Проводится до или после вечерней молитвы по местному времени.
              Akorda Palace (or The Ak Orda Presidential Palace) - Президентская Резиденция

              Акорда:  резиденция  президента  Республики  Казахстан.  Акорда  —  штаб-
              квартира Администрации Президента Казахстана. Расположена на левом берегу
              реки Ишим в столице Казахстана Астане, в начале бульвара Нуржол, в 300 метрах
              от монумента столицы Байтерек.
              Ramadan - Рамадан или Рамазан: месяц обязательного для мусульман поста,
              который является одним из  пяти столпов  ислама. В течение месяца рамадан
              правоверные  мусульмане  в  дневное  время  отказываются  от  приёма  пищи,
              питья, курения и интимной близости. Длительность месяца составляет 30 дней.

              Muslims  –  мусульмане:  люди,  придерживающиеся  ислама,  самой  молодой  и
              второй по численности приверженцев религии. Число приверженцев — около
              1,8 млрд человек, проживающих в более чем 125 странах мира. Ислам возник в
              VII веке. Основатель ислама — пророк Мухаммед. Священная книга — Коран.
                                                             89]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[Referendum  –  референдум:  важнейший  институт  прямой  демократии.

           Представляет  собой  непосредственное  правотворчество  народа.  Это  один  из
           способов участия общественности в принятии решений, важных для государства
           и для каждого отдельного гражданина. Принятое человеком решение влияет на
           результат  процедуры  и  должно  быть  подкреплено  осведомлённостью
           (информированностью) по данному вопросу.
           Constitution  of  Kazakhstan  (the  Constitution  of  the  Republic  of  Kazakhstan)  -
           Конституция  Республики  Казахстан:  основной  закон  Казахстана.  Действующая
           Конституция Республики Казахстан была принята на всенародном референдуме

           30 августа 1995 года, с поправками от 5 июня 2022 года.
           Maslikhat – маслихат: местный представительный орган в Республике Казахстан,
           избираемый населением области, города республиканского значения и столицы
           или района (региональный парламент, совет депутатов).

           VOCABULARY


                Head of State                                   major objectives
                presidential press service                      in accordance with
                the holy month of Ramadan                       spiritual development
                addressing the guests                           national culture
                spiritual self-improvement                      national identity
                good deeds                                      to exert
                socio-political life                            compatriot

                amendments                                      statesmen
                to adopt                                        public figures
                election                                        representative
                deputies                                        ethno-cultural association
                lower chamber                                   heads of foreign missions
                policy of reforms                               rescue services
                international cooperation                       nationwide referendum

                prosperity

           A. Translate the following into Russian. Consult a dictionary if necessary.
           1. This makes investors feel confident and also demonstrates our determination to
           continue the policy of reforms.
           2. Our compatriot got the bronze - for third place.
           3. Those two elements have always provided the bases for the various plans for
           international organization that have been prepared by politicians and statesmen.

           4. For example, they have abducted and detained 35 foreign journalists, as well as
           60 various political and public figures.
           5. Out of 37 Ambassadors or Heads of Foreign Missions one is woman.


                                                         90]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[6. The actual reform would be a process spanning several years, including

              constitutional elections and a nationwide referendum.
              7. According to the presidential press service, the law is aimed at improving the
              social protection of family members of the soldiers.
              8. The most important religious holiday is the holy month of Ramadan, during which
              all residents are fasting.

              B. Find in the text the English for:
              Глава государства; духовное развитие; национальная идентичность; оказывать;

              общественные  деятели;  представитель;  этнокультурное  объединение;  главы
              зарубежных  представительств;  спасательные  службы;  общенациональный
              референдум; пресс-служба президента; священный месяц Рамадан; обращение
              к гостям; добрые дела; общественно-политическая жизнь; поправки; принять;
              депутаты; нижняя палата; политика реформ; международное сотрудничество;
              процветание;  основные  цели;  добрые  дела;  поправки;  принять;  выборы;

              соотечественник;  государственные  деятели;  в  соответствии  с;  национальная
              культура;      духовное        самосовершенствование;            выборы;        общественно-
              политическая жизнь.

              C. Translate into Russian.
              President  Tokayev  Congratulates  Muslims  with  Beginning  of  Holy  Month  of
              Ramadan
              NUR-SULTAN – President Kassym-Jomart Tokayev extended congratulations over the

              beginning of the Holy Month of Ramadan to millions of Muslims around the world,
              the Akorda press service reports.
              The holy month of Ramadan, which commemorates the revelation of the Quran to
              the Prophet Muhammad, begins April 13 and will last through May 12.
              During this ninth month of the lunar Islamic calendar month, Muslims around the
              world abstain from drinking, eating, smoking and sexual relations.
              “For Muslims, it is a period of spiritual renewal and purification. Oraza (Ramadan in

              Kazakh) calls for mutual respect and mercy, forgiveness and kindness. People strive
              to help those in need, make donations and do good,” said Tokayev.
              The spiritual values contribute to strengthening the unity and solidarity of society, he
              added.
              As this year the holy month will be celebrated in unusual circumstances, its meaning
              becomes ever more important.
              “All measures are being taken to curb the pandemic. I urge all Muslims in our country
              to observe the safety requirements and strictly follow the recommendations of the

              Spiritual Board of Muslims of Kazakhstan,” said the President.
              Kazakh Prime Minister Askar Mamin also congratulated the nation on the occasion,
              reports his press service.


                                                             91]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[“Ramadan strengthens the traditional spiritual values of the people of Kazakhstan,

           which  unites  not  only  Muslims  but  also  representatives  of  other  religions  in  our
           country. I wish good health, peace and well-being to all the people of Kazakhstan,” he
           said.
           As community plays an important part in the celebration of the month, Kazakhstan’s
           Spiritual Administration of Muslims said it would give online lectures and conduct
           virtual prayers, as gatherings remain prohibited.
           “An online program to conduct sermons, religious lectures, celebrate Laylat al-Qadr,
           or the night of predestination and during the great Oraza Ayt (end of Ramadan) has

           been prepared. It is possible to get an answer to a question online, listen to an online
           sermon  and  do  good  deeds  from  the  comfort  of  one’s  home.  Given  the  current
           situation, we will continue the project we implemented last year for online donations
           of  sadaqah  and  zakat,”  said  Chair  of  the  Spiritual  Administration  of  Muslims  of
           Kazakhstan  and  Supreme  Mufti  Nauryzbai  kazhi  Taganuly  during  an  online  press
           briefing.

           Last year, the holy month of Ramadan witnessed tighter restrictions, when movement
           was limited to grocery and pharmacy shopping and gatherings were prohibited.
           By Assel Satubaldina for The Astana Times, April 13, 2022
           Link: https://astanatimes.com/2021/04/president-tokayev-congratulates-muslims-
           with-beginning-of-holy-month-of-ramadan/




























                                                         92]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[REFERENCES


              1.  Фромкин,  В.  Тіл  біліміне  кіріспе  /  В.  Фромкин,  Р.  Родман,  Н.  Хайамс;  ред.
              алқасының төрағасы М.М. Тәжин. - 10-шы бас. - Астана: Ұлттық аударма бюросы,
              2018. - 608 с. - (Рухани жаңғыру)
              2. Жұмабекова, А.Қ. Аударма теориясы: Оқу құралы. / Шет тілдер және іскерлік

              карьера университеті. - Алматы, 2015. - 267 б. - ISBN 978-9965-20-786-0.
              3.  Семенов,  А.Л.  Теория  перевода:  Учебник.  -  2-е  изд.,  испр.  и  доп.  -  М.:
              Издательский центр “Академия”, 2013. - 224c. - (Сер. Высшее профессиональное
              образование. Бакалавриат). -ISBN 978-5-7695-9334-5.
              4. Әжібекова, Г.Ж. English for Banking and Finance: Оқу құралы. - Алматы: ҚазҰТУ,
              2013. - 98б. -ISBN 978–601–228–486–7.

              5.  Beisembayeva,  A.D.  Recommendations  to  practical  classes.  «Translation  of
              Economic texts» for 5B020700 – Translation Studies speciality / A. D. Beisembayeva,
              G. K. Ertayeva, B. M. Mukasheva. - Версия. - Shymkent: SKSU named after M. Auezov,
              2018 o=эл. опт.диск (CD-ROM)
              6. Шевелева, С.А. Английский язык для банковских работников. Основной курс /
              С. А. Шевелева, О. Б. Кокорина, Л. В. Аверьянова. - 4-е изд., испр. и доп. - М.:
              Филоматис, 2007. - 328 с.
              7.  Агабекян,  И.П.  English  for  Managers.  Английский  язык  для  менеджеров:

              Учебное пособие / И. П. Агабекян. - М.: ТК Велби, Изд-во Проспект, 2008. - 352 с.
              - (На рус., англ. яз.)
              8.  Kaldybekkyzy,  M. Methodical  recommendations  for  the  study  of discipline  and
              content  of  the  course  “The  practice  of  literary  translation”:  for  students  in  the
              specialty 5B020700 - English Linguistics / M. Kaldybekkyzy, A. D. Beisembayeva . -
              Версия . - Shymkent: SKSU named after M. Auezov, 2016 o=эл. опт. диск (CD-ROM)
              9.  Рамазанова,  Г.Х.  Пояснение  в  структуре  художественного  текста:  учебно-

              методическое пособие для студ. спец. 5В020700 – “Переводческое дело” / Г. Х.
              Рамазанова. - Алматы: New Book, 2018. - 96 с.
              10. Zhaulbayeva, A.A. Recommendations to practical classes on discipline “Written
              translation practice” speciality 5B020700 – Translation study / A. A. Zhaulbayeva. -
              Shymkent: SKSU named after M. Auezov, 2012 o=эл. опт. диск (CD-ROM)

               11. www.bbc.com                                 16. www.hbr.org
               12. www.cnn.com                                 17. www.voanews.com

               13. www.astanatimes.com                         18. www.nbc.com
               14. www.theguardian.com                         19. www.cbsnews.com
               15. www.new.ske.com                             20. https://www.fairobserver.com





                                                             93]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[AUTHORS









                     Жантуреева Гульсара Арынбековна








                       Жусубалина Жанат Мейрбековна


























































                                                         94]]></page><page Index="95"/></pages></Search>
